In this video I’d
like to show you 2 or 3 tips
for Nautilus.
So let’s start by opening it.
The first thing is that you see
packages
with triangles and packages
without triangles.
if I click on the triangle,
we see that
inside there are names.
What does that mean?
If I click on AST-Core,
I can see all the
classes containing this
package, as well as
extensions, as I told you before
and
then I see names.
In fact I have what we
call tags, these are not packages,
these are not
sub-packages, these are only
logical groups of classes.
For a certain reason, the developer
has chosen that, to browse
his package, it would be easier
to represent classes,
first with all classes,
and second
with the organisation that
suits him.
For instance, here there is
Formatter, there are 2 code
Formatter for Pharo. Here on Nodes
there are all the nodes
of the abstract syntax tree.
Here there is the Parser, and there
Tokens for example, and Visitors.
You can see that very quickly,
when you want to do something,
you can go directly on the right category.
So here now,
I would like to show you
how you can filter
the information
Nautilus gives you and how
you can create groups to
manage your development.
Let’s open Nautilus.
If I type for instance Collections,
I will get collections,
I will get all the packages
which have the word Collections
either in their name or in their tag.
If we look here, there is this.
So this is very helpful.
You can also associate them,
there I can have all
packages containing
Morph and Collections.
There is also another way to do
it, let’s imagine
we work on Fuel. Fuel is Pharo’s
Serializer.
I take all the Fuel packages and
I put them in another group.
So here I put it in a Work
group, it means
that next time I will open
Nautilus, I will
have a group named Work.
In this Work group I have
all my Fuel packages that will
offer me exactly the same
functionalities than before.
So it is quite practical,
I don’t have to write a
search each time,
I know I have this.
In the same way, if you click
on Work and
you create a new group,
you can call it
MyNewGroup, and for instance
if you want to add
Core inside, you do
"Add in group" “MyNewGroup” and
you will have your package inside.