In this session, I'll introduce blocks.
They're sort of anonymous methods
also called lexical closures.
They're everywhere in Pharo.
They're the base of loops,
conditionals, iterators,
and even GUIs or dedicated languages.
They're at the heart of the system.
They've only been introduced
in the latest version of Java.
To define a block, use square brackets.
This an example:
[expressions...]
We'll talk about block definition.
Another example:
this expression, 1/0,
returns an error when executed.
Let's encapsulate it in a block
by defining a block that contains
the expression 1/0.
If I evaluate this block's definition,
nothing happens: no error.
It returns the block
as a block definition
doesn't execute its body.
You can define as many blocks
as you wish:
the expressions in its body are frozen.
To evaluate a block
and the expressions in its body,
you must do it explicitly
through the message value.
For instance, this is a block:
[2 + 6]
You send it the message value.
The expressions in the body
are evaluated.
It returns the result, 8.
However, if the block
contains erroneous expressions,
the error is returned
when the block is evaluated,
as in the example 2.
[1/0]: I send the message value
to the block.
It returns an error.
Blocks can also take arguments
as in this argument.
It's just like methods.
A block is always opened by [
and closed by ].
All the arguments are prefixed
by a colon.
Then there's |, a pipe.
It separates the argument declaration
from the block's body,
the expressions it contains.
The argument in this example is x.
x + 2 is the only expression
in the block.
If I send the message value
to the block,
you have to use a specific message,
value: with a parameter.
At the same time, you pass the value 5
which replaces the argument x
when the expressions of the block
are evaluated.
If I send the message value: 5
to this block,
it returns 7
since the value of x is 5
when the block is evaluated.
This is like my previous example,
but with several expressions
in the block.
I have two here: x+33 and x+2.
When I send value: 5
to evaluate the expressions
in the block,
the evaluation returns
only the value of the last expression
in the block.
It only returns the result of x+2,
7.
Blocks are normal objects in Pharo.
They can be stored
in temporary variables.
They can be sent messages
like normal objects.
This is the example I have for you here.
You can store the definition
of this block, x+2,
in a variable called add2.
Then you send messages
to evaluate the block several times.
I send the message value: once
by telling it to evaluate itself
with the value 5: it returns 7.
Then the message value: 33.
It returns 35.
You can also define blocks
with several arguments.
For instance, x and y.
This block has two arguments.
But how would you evaluate this block
since you need to pass two values
to trigger its evaluation,
5 and 7 which would replace x and y?
The answer is that you use
the message value: value:,
a method of the class block.
5 replaces x and 7 replaces y.
It returns 12.
Like methods, blocks
can also define temporary variables.
This example is an actual example:
it comes from the class Collection.
The block starts here.
It ends there.
It takes one argument called :index.
It takes one temporary variable
defined here between two |.
It's called args.
This temporary variable args
exists only during the evaluation
of the expressions in the block.
Blocks are defined in methods.
In a block, you can also use a return.
This is an example
from the class Integer.
The method is called factorial.
There are several blocks in the method.
These blocks contain returns, or ^.
The return helps
to exit the method factorial.
For instance, if I send the message
factorial to the integer 0,
it returns the answer 1.
I get this answer thanks to this ^,
the first in the block,
which helps
to exit the method factorial.
A return in a block helps
to exit the method
which defines the block.
A piece of advice
for when you use blocks:
blocks are extremely powerful elements.
You must use them carefully.
Don't go beyond two to three arguments
for one block.
If you have more,
it becomes incomprehensible.
It's better to define a class
with instance variables and methods:
it'll be much more legible.
In the course, we studied blocks,
their syntax,
the fact they were some sort
of anonymous methods,
that is, lexical closures;
they can be stored in variables
as they're like any other object.
In other lessons, we'll see that blocks
are the basis of many constructions
such as loops, iterations, etc.