In this video, I'd like to
explain a little bit
Pharo's different packaging
ways, in order for
not to get lost in the future.
When you install Pharo, you will
normally click on a link
given, but if you go on
Pharo,
the release at the moment
of this video
is version 4, but version 5 will
be exactly the same.
When I downloaded Mac OSX version,
I get this zip.
If I unzip this zip,
I get what I call Pharo4 app.
When I launch
Pharo 4 app, I get Pharo.
Let's imagine we write
"Hello". When I save,
it will save the environment.
I click on Save.
If I click on Quit now,
I will launch it again,
and I will have exactly
"Hello", because saving the Pharo
image is making a memory copy
with all the
objects included Bytecode objects
and compiled methods.
What is there in
this application?
On Mac, we can what is inside.
If I click on Show Contents,
what will I see?
I'm going ti find a Pharo virtual
machine and ressources.
And here, I will find a changes
file and an
image file.
The image file is the one that
really contains
the objects representing the memory,
and the changes file
is a file comprising all the
incremental changes
done.
If I double-click
on the image file,
normally, depending on the
OS, I will launch it on
a Pharo virtual machine that
I have installed, it
will launch again my image file.
This image file,
what happens with it?
Let's imagine I define a classe.
I'm going to define a package,
"Add package" "ATest".
In this package,
I'm going to define
"MyStrangeClass".
I define it and here, I put
"foooo" which returns
42.
If I save this image with
another name, I'm going
to save it with the name
Pharo40Stef.
What did it do?
I quit. It created another
pair
image and change. In this changes
file, we won't open it
because it is not readable
by a human, there is
the methods code I have just
created.
And if I launch again Pharo 4,
I'm gonna
launch it using the virtual
machine, I get
once more the snapshot, what
we call the system
copy that I had done at a certain
moment
before.
Now, if I execute again
PharoStef image, what will it
do?
It will show me the system
with my new class.
The Pharo 4 application,
it is what we call a Mac
bundle which contains the Pharo
VM plus an image plus a change.
If I double-click on it,
I don't have any choice, it
will always choose Pharo image
because it is a script
that has coded:
"Here it is, this is THAT image."
In general, it is useful at
the beginning of the use of
Pharo, but we do not use it.
In general, either we use an
instruction of the command
line which is something like
Pharo-ui with
MyPharoImage.image
and this will
send the thing. Or if we use
command line and we
don't want to have the ui, we
will do that kind of things.
It means that Pharo is installed
somewhere in
your system as a standard Unix
application.
Now, you see on this page
that you can download a
Pharo
pair, you can
download a virtual machine.
We are gonna download the
virtual machine and
download an image pair
and also source.
I'm gonna explain what it is,
this way we will have the
3 at hand, we will play together.
Now if I unzip the file
corresponding to
Pharo Image and
Changes, I get this one.
When I unzip, what do I get in
Pharo in this file?
I get an image.
We will do it in a mode where
you can
see what is inside.
It means that this file,
it is again an image pair
corresponding to a certain
state of the snapshot or of the
Pharo image, of the virtualised
system. Here, I can execute it
on the Pharo image.
I get a message,
what is this message?
The system can work since
I can execute anything.
I can run it.
Now, I can do exactly what I
did before.
I can define MyPackage,
and in MyPackage
I will say MyStrangeClass.
So we start to be used to it.
I define a method:
fooo 42. It asks for my
login.
I can do as usual
"MyStrangeClass
new fooo" and I get 42.
So, very good. I can save.
I save it for example with
another name,
Stef, I name it
PharoStrange.
OK.
What does it say?
It says “I can’t find the source
file
Pharo 4. 0." Why does it say this?
When I open the briwser, if I can
see for instance the
AST code, this is not your code,
so we go at the top.
The reason why the system
doesn’t find the comments
is that it is decompiling.
So, we don’t see it because the methods
are
too simple, but it decompiles
the code.
Let’s go on something more
concrete.
Here it decompiled the code,
the Bytecode represents an
an argument and it knows very well
that this is an argument.
But we lost the source.
In general, the sytem source,
when Pharo
is implemented, is stored in
a file called Pharo 4 source
that you can find here.
In genral Pharo 4
source will be installed once
on the system because
this file is on read only,
and all your
applications can use it.
I have it here, I’m gonna unzipp it.
Here I have Pharo4.source.
If I quit without saving
and I relaunch the application,
here anyway you see
that it does exactly the same as
previously, it is to say
that when I save a snapshot
giving it
another name, I have once more
a system with 2 things:
the image and its changes.
Here if I take my old image,
there
is no more error because
it has found the code and it
knows that it corresponds to
the state there was
when we launched the first image.
Now if I use the second one,
if I consider the file
AST-Core, first
my classes have comments.
Here these are really the names
people gave.
If we look at this architecture,
what do we have?
We have the source file
containing the system sources,
in general, once the system is
compiled, the compiler
doesn’t need the sources,
the virtual machine and
image and change pairs.
Image contains all the objects
that have been defined plus
the system objects,
with the changes files which
contains the deltas of what you’ve done
compared to the changes file.
Each time you save you system,
it is
as if you save a virtualised
image of your OS.
This is exactly the same principle.
If you look inside the Pharo 4
application,
you will find those ressources.
I have the Pharo 4 sources,
I have the image file,
the changes file and somewhere
here the virtual
machine with its plugins.