In this video, I’d like
to show you that we can
browse, compute the differences
between the
committed package versions
on a repository.
Here, I’m gonna use a local
repository.
So this means that if you don’t
use Small Talk hub and
and you work with a team,
you can compute
the differences and merges of codes that
you can share with others.
I use Monticello,
this is why I have in fact
versioned many versions
of this package.
I open, I click on Open.
Here, I see all the versions
of my package.
Now if I consider the last
version,
I can browse, it means I
want to see
what is inside the package
which is on the repository.
If I do “Browse”, you see that
I have the very last
package version.
And it shows the extensions:
“You are extending this.”
Now if I consider an older
version, like
this one, and I browse,
we will see that I only
have 2 classes left and
I haven’t any extensions.
You already see, I can
look at what
is published on a server and
go and see the content inside.
Now in my image,
I have the latest version so
I can compare the changes.
It means that I can see
“Give me the changes
between this image and what is
loaded in the system.”
The system warns us:
“Careful, if you
load this package, it will
suppress all these methods”,
and obviously I want to see
the methods.
Now I can,
when using the “history button”,
for example if I want to
know what
has happened between version 7
and version 4.
I choose version 7, I click on
History, it
shows me several versions.
I go from version 4, so I
select
version 4 and I say
“I want to see
the changes
to version 7.”
And here, it shows
“Here is what you have done.”
So obviously, here I have only
added things
but if I had modified, for
example, if I had modified
a method category and protocol,
it would show
me all the changes.
In the same way, if I want to see
what happened
between version 11 and
version 8 for instance…
here I added + and
that kind of thing.
You can see that in Pharo you
have all the tools
allowing you to manage a project
with several members.
Further more, you will have
all the access rights managed
by the different systems,
such as Small Talk Hub or
Squick Source, and you can
work in group very
on Pharo.
By the way, this is how
Pharo itself is being developped.