I’d like to show you the
Pharo Launcher.
Pharo Launcher is a tool
developped
independently from Pharo and
which, in the end, will replace
Pharo App that we have seen in the
other session about understanding exchange.
This is an application that
enables to manage
a whole set of images, and
above all to access to all
the integration servers which
will enable you, each
time you commit, to recreate
an
image and to download it
very easily.
I typed PharoLauncher
in Google to show you.
If you go on Inria Jenkins,
what do you get?
You get this page.
There is an official website.
Ok, the official website is
on SmallTalk Hub.
And here if I want to install
on Mac OS X
I will
download a .dmg.
If I unzip the .dmg,
I get an application named
Pharo and that should be named
Pharo Launcher, it would be better.
Something is nice in this application,
and I personnaly use it
all the time,
it shows you (normally when you
will launch it
you won’t see anything)…
For me here, it shows all the things
I have installed on my system.
What is very nice, it is that on
the left, this
list, these are the images
on which I am
working, and on the right,
these are
shortcuts, for example you
can get the
Pharo version 5 Beta,
the stable version 4.
So this one, these are my favorites ones.
Next, you can access to all
images you
have downloaded recently
and that are stored
locally, in order for you
not to need to
download from the server,
because it can be
troublesome depending on your
internet connexion.
Mine being slow,
it is troublesome.
So, you have that sort of things.
Now, what is great, it is
that you have
access to Pharo Contribution Jenkins.
What is it?
It is a Jenkins server
on which people can
store a certain number of projects,
you just have to
ask to get an access.
There are many things, I don’t
know precisely what they are.
You can choose
different versions.
I am going to show you Seaside,
the dynamic web
application server,
I have, for example, all the build.
For one build, I get the message
“do you want a Pharo 2.0,
a Pharo 3.0,
a Pharo 4.0 version,
in BleedInEdge, under development,
under release, under release
1.3.
I won’t get it because I have
it already
but what is great,
so I have it here,
if I tell it to create an image,
I call it Seaside, here
it extracts
the image from my cache and
it goes here, and now I can execute it.
And here, I have my Seaside image.
What is great, if you look
a little bit at Seaside,
Seaside is quite big,
there are all these
packages in the system
with I don’t know how many
classes
to download.
So, it is very practical because
what is great, I will take
another example…
if I exit, now I am working on…
I have Smalltalk mathematic
library, called
Sci-Smalltalk, I have my environment.
Each time I commit code from this
this image, on the
repository of Sci-Smalltalk,
there will be a Jenkins job
that will see it and
rebuild the image, and
propose me to download it
after having run tests.
So here, if I go in contribution
and I look for
Sci-Smalltalk,
this is the same, I have all the builds
with the different Pharo versions.
Here, there are fewer.
There are 4.0
under stable development,
5.0 under unstable development.
If I want to get one,
I will download it.
I do “Create image”
And automatically, I can
get the last
configuration loaded,
according to
configurations and to
how I have configured my Jenkins job.
Pharo Launcher, I strongly encourage you
to use it
because it is really great.
In conclusion, Pharo Launcher
is really very nice
because it combines at the same time
the access to your jobs and
the organisation on your system files.
When you work on several projects,
it is always nice to have an
overview on your projects.
Pharo Launcher has been developped
by Damien Cassou,
who is one of the three authors
of this MOOC, and I really
thank him for this, it is really cool.