Hello.
Today we are going
to talk about messages.
You'll see why having lots of messages
and small methods is good.
Contrary to what
many developers believe.
This slide illustrates
a design sequence.
This is valid not only for Pharo,
but for design
in any object-oriented language.
As you know,
message sends are hooks,
places where we can define behavior.
Developers often say
that they like big methods because
they're easy to understand.
You read the lines
and you understand the code.
But in this session I will show you
that this is not such a good thing.
In general,
big methods mean bad design.
A hierarchy of classes
and a same method
implemented in several classes,
is one means of defining choices.
If I take a fat class
with lots of operations,
and I have to choose
an operation according to status,
my code will say: "If I'm in this state,
I do this operation.
"If I'm in that state,
I do that operation."
You'll have big codes
with IFs all over the place.
This means that
when you want to add new cases,
you have to modify methods everywhere.
In the version on the right-hand side,
the operation for each case
is divided into a specific class.
All you have to do
is send an operation message
to an object to create an IF.
The IF does not need to be written
by the programmer.
It's done automatically
via the polymorphism principle.
In the following slides, I'll show you
how to improve one example
by changing small bits at a time.
Here is a big method
that is not easy to understand
and which does many things.
Here's what we want to do.
In a subclass,
we want to give this variable here
a different value.
As it's set up,
the only way to do that
is to create the subclass,
then duplicate all of the code,
adding the small modification
you want to make.
In languages like Java
that use private keywords,
if the attributes
used by the method are private,
what I just did is impossible.
If the method uses
instance variables that are private,
subclasses cannot duplicate code.
But in any case,
duplicating is not good practice,
because duplication copies bugs too.
If I have a bug in my original version,
I'll have a bug in my copies.
And if I modify one copy,
I have to modify every duplication.
It's extra work for the developer
and you must remember
that there are various copies.
The real solution is sending messages.
In a method, when you send a message
rather than writing
the content of the
corresponding method directly inside,
subclasses can override behavior.
If we look at the bar method,
it sends foo to self.
In A, foo returns 10,
but the subclasses
can override this value
and replace it with 42, for example.
So how can we improve
the code you just saw
and benefit from
the inheritance mechanism
without using duplication?
I'm going to extract this part here
and send a message instead.
It's done by a refactoring function
called extract method.
You have tools to transform this code
into this code here.
The code I selected
in the previous slide
was transferred
into a new method called ratio.
And here where the code was written,
we now have a message send.
This means that in the subclasses,
I can change this behavior.
Either change it completely
or recall the behavior of the superclass
and make a modification.
That's what I'm doing here.
I send a ratio message to super
to execute the code as it is
in the superclass,
and I add 10,
which is what my goal was.
Another possible method
is to extract this part here,
so that the subclasses
can change this behavior.
I extract this piece of code
into a specific method.
And in the primary method,
I send a message.
In this case,
the class we want
an instance variable for is in hardcode.
This means that if the subclasses
want to change this class,
to potentially get a UINode subclass,
it will have to duplicate
the entire method.
Here we can use the same process
and extract the class into a method,
so that the subclasses
can change the instance variable.
That's what I'm doing here.
I extract the part that interests me
into a method,
and I send a message.
Sending a message enables the subclasses
to change behavior.
Like I said earlier,
certain programmers
do not agree with this approach.
They find it difficult to read lots of
small, spread out methods.
They'd rather read a big method
line by line.
This isn't good practice,
because reading code line by line
won't work
if the application is very big.
You can't read line by line
and understand what's going on.
This is where abstractions are useful
and extracting bits of behavior
or expressions from methods
makes sense.
You can read a method globally
without understanding every detail.
So little methods are good,
you should use them everywhere.
Let's carry on.
Here we see that
the value 55 appears in hardcode
in the method code.
This means the subclasses
cannot change to 100, for example.
So we will extract this value
like we did previously,
and put it in a separate method so that
the subclasses can change the value.
Another advantage is that previously
the value 55 was written here.
Now it's called self averageRatio.
This means we replaced
a numerical value by a name,
and I now know what
the value 55 corresponds to.
I know it means averageRatio
and when I read the code, I understand.
So having many small methods
helps to read the code.
Creating an averageRatio method
to return 55
enables all subclasses
to change values.
But how can we let class users
change their value too?
What we can do,
is use an instance variable.
The averageRatio method
used in the previous slide
will return the value
of the instance variable,
if it contains a value.
If not, it returns the default value.
The default value was 55.
And the users of a node object
can program
whatever value they like inside.
With this design,
subclasses can override
the defaultAverageRatio
and change the value.
And class users can set a value
by executing the program.
This is called
gruyere-oriented programming.
An object-oriented program,
a WIN method,
contains holes called hooks,
which can be filled with subclasses.
As a conclusion,
code can be reused
and refined in subclasses.
Each time we send a message,
subclasses can change
the behavior of the superclass:
Refine it or completely change it.
Small methods are great because
they give names to bits of expressions,
and because they give subclasses
the freedom to change behavior.