-Hi. In this video, we are going to look
at how we can look for a class in Pharo,
so how to use the Spotter tool.
You can access the Spotter tool
by going to Tools, Spotter.
This will open the Spotter,
but you can also press Shift+Enter
and it will open the Spotter as well.
If you search for a class named "Point",
for example,
and simply write "Point",
then go to Classes and double click,
this will open the System Browser
on the correct class.
Now, if you go back
to calling the Spotter,
so Shift+Enter,
it will save the history
of your searches,
so you will have the last call
to the class stored.
This will really help you
access something
you just opened and closed,
and you would like to open again.
So, Shift+Enter, then press back Enter,
and this will open the last class
you just searched for.
We will look into more tips
about the Spotter in the next videos.