Hello. This sequence
is about the Pharo Web Stack.
I'll give you an overview
of existing frameworks
and the ones we'll be using
in this course.
This is a diagram of what happens
to an incoming HTTP request.
"Zinc" is the basic HTTP/HTTPS
server built into Pharo.
Teapot is above Zinc,
and there is a course available
on Teapot syntax.
Then, there's a series of format
frameworks, like JSON and Stone.
There's also Seaside REST.
Briefly, it's how to program REST
over Seaside.
Seaside is the web framework
we will be using
in Tinyblog.
That's why we introduced
Seaside to you, as well.
It is in widespread use in businesses.
We will also use Voyage,
which is a persistence framework
for documents.
We take our objects and store them
in document form, in Mongo bases.
There are others, of course.
Garage is a sort of driver
for all relational databases.
I'll also show you Magritte.
Magritte is a way
of describing data
and generating webforms
automatically, as a result,
instead of manually.
Reef is an application
that enables you
to do embarked JavaScript
in web components.
But we won't go into it further
in this course.
Mustache is a template system
that generates HTML on the fly.
Bootstrap is
the Twitter Bootstrap library,
fully integrated into Seaside.
These are the most
commonly used applications,
but you have plenty of other packages
on top of Pharo.
The ones used to connect to Amazon
or to do elastic searches, for example.
We will be using Seaside.
It's a web framework
for building dynamic applications
based on reusable components.
We don't really have to
manage requests.
Seaside does it for us.
Documentation is available
at Seaside.st.
The site is being rebuilt.
They have also compiled
a 250-page reference book
at book.seaside.st.
You can take a look, but we'll cover
the main points here
in this course.
Regarding persistence,
as I said earlier,
there are two major frameworks
that enable you to store documents
in NoSQL.
They are based on components
like Mongo, CouchDB, and Riak.
We use Voyage as an abstraction
on top of MongoDB.
And Garage is a framework
offering a unified API
for relational databases.
We won't use it in this course,
but it has drivers
for Postgres, MySQL, SQLite,
and OpenDBX.
And it is always being improved.
We are going to show you
another interesting feature.
We have a framework called Magritte,
for the surrealist painter.
It writes descriptions for your data
and use them to generate
Seaside components.
It really helps boost productivity
in creating web applications.
To conclude, I would say
Pharo offers a rich ecosystem.
Most of the companies using Pharo
are web developers.
It is business-ready.
Seaside is really innovative,
because it goes against certain
entrenched ways of programming.
It helps you think differently.