Hello, everyone.
This is the fifth sequence
on inheritance and lookup.
We'll be covering
messaging
and lookup algorithms
for metaclasses.
In Pharo,
everything is an object,
and objects
can receive messages.
So classes are objects, too.
And since objects
can receive messages,
classes can receive messages.
The messaging mechanism
is exactly the same,
whether the receiver is a class
or other object.
There is only one way
to look up a method.
This is the lookup algorithm
we've seen several times
in earlier sessions.
Now let's look at the example
of messaging a class.
Understand
the basic principle:
Since classes are objects,
and each object
is linked to a class,
that is,
an instance of a class,
aNode is an instance
of Node class.
Since Node class
is an object,
Node class is an instance
of another class.
It is called Node class.
So, aNode is an instance
of Node class,
and Node class is an object
that is an instance of Node class class.
If that's the way it is,
you may wonder
Node class is a class; a class
is an object, an instance of a class.
which class Node class
is an instance of.
You will see that in the next sequence,
on metaclasses.
Here are a few examples.
Here, the object, aWorkstation,
is an instance of Workstation class.
Workstation is a subclass of Node,
a subclass of Object.
Here, you must
pay attention to the arrows.
The arrow with a blank tip
indicates a subclass relationship.
Node is a subclass of Object.
Workstation
is a subclass of Node.
The arrow with a black point,
is sometimes represented
as a simple two-line arrow, too.
It indicates instanciation.
aWorkstation is an instance
of Workstation.
Workstation is an instance
of Workstation class.
Likewise, Object
is an instance of Object class.
If I message
the object aWorkstation,
the lookup algorithm searches
the aWorkstation class.
Then it goes up
through superclasses
until it finds
a matching method.
The mechanism
is exactly the same
when I message
the Workstation class.
For example, if I send the message
"new"
to Workstation,
the lookup algorithm
searches Workstation class
for a method called "new."
If it finds it here,
it executes it.
If it does not find a match,
it moves up to the superclass,
and then up
to the next superclass.
And so on.
This hierarchy continues.
I'll leave you with this slide
summing up messaging
to standard objects
and classes as standard objects.
Here's what to remember:
A class is an object
like any other.
Messages can be sent to objects,
and therefore to classes.
The lookup mechanism
is exactly the same in both cases.
It starts searching
in the class of the receiver,
and then searches each superclass
in the inheritance chain
until it finds a matching method.
You'll learn more about metaclasses
in "Understanding Metaclasses."