Hello to all.
This sequence
will focus on class methods.
As we saw earlier,
class methods are normal methods,
like other methods.
Generally, they are used
to create new instances,
but can be used for other things.
We'll be seeing two examples
of uses for class methods.
Imagine we want to parse
these lines
in a computer program.
The lines create a structure.
If a line starts
with an exclamation point,
it is read as a title.
Lines that start with dashes
are list items.
Lines that start
with more than one dash
are subitems on a list.
In any other case, it is a paragraph.
Take a program with this input:
It creates instances
for the classes here,
subclasses of DocumentItem.
We also want to design
this program
so that each subclass
of DocumentItem is responsible
for parsing lines,
and for deciding "canParse" (or cannot)
for a given line.
In the "canParse" method here,
we submit a line of text.
If the line starts
with an exclamation point,
the canParse method must return True.
The line belongs
to the Section Title class.
In the ListItem class,
the canParse method returns True
if the line starts with a dash.
And the canParse line we see here
must always return True.
The idea is to write an algorithm
that looks at classes one by one.
As soon as one returns
canParse for a given line,
we use that class to create
a new instance for that line.
That's the goal of canParse method.
The newFromLine method also
takes a line of text as a parameter.
But it returns an instance in the class
in which the line is implemented.
If I send a newFromLine message
to the SectionTitle class,
with a chain of characters
starting with an exclamation point,
the newFromLine method will return
an instance of the SectionTitle class.
This is what happens:
The ClassParser does this work.
It searches
DocumentItem subclasses
for the one
in charge of a given line.
The Parser has a method
called documentClasses.
Its goal is to return
the list of Subclasses
in DocumentItem.
It returns a collection
containing these three classes.
We do this by sending the message
"allSubclasses" to DocumentItem.
The allSubclasses method
already exists in the Pharo system.
It returns the list of subclasses
in a given class.
That message yields a collection
containing SectionTitle,
ListItem, and Text.
I want the collection
sorted by priority.
The idea is for the text class
to come at the end
because its canParse method
always returns True.
The text class
can parse any line at random.
We will test that method
after testing the others.
We have the concept
of priority here.
As you see, many methods
are underlined.
If I underline the methods here,
this indicates they are class methods.
To execute these methods,
the message must be sent to the Class.
I must send the canParse method
to the SectionTitle class
to find out if the SectionTitle class
can parse a given line.
The Parse method of the Parser class
takes a line as a parameter.
It searches all DocumentItem subclasses
for a class that can parse the line.
If it detects one, it creates an instance
of this class.
Sending the command "detect:"
to a collection
yields one among n elements
in a collection, following a predicate.
Now we'll look at another example
of using class methods.
We'll look at how command-line
parameters are handled.
Here we see a program
receiving parameters,
detecting the parameters
that will make it do things differently.
The first parameter indicates
the action to be carried out.
We will design the program so that
we have one class per action type.
The "eval" action is represented
by one class:
eval CommandLineHandler.
What action is carried out
when the "eval" parameter appears?
It executes...
This chain of characters
is interpreted as Pharo code,
and return the result
of the expression.
3628800 is the result
of 10 factorial.
This is implemented
using the Command-Line Handler
class.
EvaluateCommandLineHandler
is a subclass
assigned to processing
the "eval" parameter.
If "eval" is sent as the first parameter
in a command line,
this class has to work.
The isReponsibleFor method
must return True
if there is one subclass
capable of taking the command line
into account.
Underneath, we see
a mechanism identical to the one
we saw in the preceding example.
Once again, we are using class methods
and sending messages to classes
for tasks other than creating instances.
This sequence showed us
two possible uses for class methods.
Class methods
are mostly used to create new instances.
But they can also be used
in other cases.