Hello, everyone.
Welcome to Sequence 1 of Week 4.
This week, we'll be covering
Pharo inheritance basics,
and look-up
and web-development mechanisms.
In the first sequence,
we'll introduce inheritance basics.
These concepts are quite similar
to inheritance
in other languages with classes,
like Java.
Even if you are familiar
with these basics, please watch.
We'll introduce some vocabulary,
and a graphic representation
you'll be seeing again
throughout the rest of the course.
This sequence will cover
what inheritance is,
and how to use it.
Two classes are represented
on the right:
the Rectangle class,
with its name, first of all,
its instance variables,
and its methods.
Under it, you see the same thing.
The class name, ColoredRectangle,
its instance variables, and its methods.
The vertical arrow here, with
its point represented as a blank triangle,
indicates an inheritance relationship.
The ColoredRectangle subclass
inherits from the Rectangle class.
Generally, subclasses like
ColoredRectangle
refine the behavior and state
of their superclass.
A subclass like ColoredRectangle
can add state and behavior
to its superclass.
Here, the ColoredRectangle class
adds state
in the form of two instance variables,
color and border color.
It also adds a method: color.
At some point, we could say
that every class
inherits from the Object class.
But that's not quite true.
It is true that every class
inherits from ProtoObject class.
The ProtoObject superclass
is used for very special cases.
For the purposes of this course
in Pharo,
we'll say that all classes inherit
from Object.
That will suffice, for our needs.
The ProtoObject class is reserved
only for certain specific cases.
You're not likely to need it
to learn the basics of Pharo.
Inheritance behaves
in two different ways,
depending on whether state
or behavior is being inherited.
Inheritance of state is static.
That means that
when you create the subclass,
you know exactly what
all the instance variables are.
However, inheritance of behavior
is dynamic.
During the program's execution,
you look at the methods
defined in sub and superclasses.
Concerning instance variables,
inheritance happens
during class definition.
When you define the subclass,
you take the instance variables
defined in the subclass -
here, they are color and border color,
and you merge them
with all the instance variables
defined in the superclass
and the line of the superclasses,
all the way up to the Object.
Here, the instance variables
of ColoredRectangle
will be with a color and border color.
For behavior,
inheritance mechanism changes.
Watch the following sequences
to see exactly how it occurs.
So, on the whole,
behavior inheritance happens at runtime.
In other words, when you send
a message to an object,
a method match is searched for
in the class hierarchy.
Here, if I send a message
to ColoredRectangle...
The "area" message, for example...
it will be searched in the class.
The method will be searched
in the ColoredRectangle class.
The "area" method is missing.
So we go up to the superclass.
We find the "area" method.
It is selected and executed.
Now, I'll sum up:
For inheritance, the concepts
of subclass and superclass
enables the subclass
to refine the behavior
of its superclass, and extend it.
The subclass can also extend, or add,
state to its superclass.
Pharo's simple inheritance model
stipulates one superclass per class.
The concept of traits
enables you multiply inheritance,
but we will not cover that.
Object is at the top of the hierarchy.
So is ProtoObject,
but we will not go into that detail.
Inheritance of state is static.
It happens when the subclass is defined.
But inheritance of behavior is dynamic,
happening at runtime,
whenever you send a message
to an object.