-Hi. In this video, we are going to look
at the automated tools Pharo provides
to critique your code and give you some
direct feedback or automated feedback.
For example, I loaded the MyCounter
we developed in the redo of week 2.
If you go to Counter and, for example,
the increment method,
if we write some debugging code,
if we leave some debugging code
such as "self halt", so a breakpoint.
If we save this,
we will see a warning there saying
that there is some debugging code
left in the method,
and you can look on the question mark,
click on this,
it will explain what this really is. So:
"Breakpoints, logging statements, etc.
should not be left in production code".
You can click on the tools
to get a direct resolve of issues.
Let's click on it.
You can see that this tool modified
the increment method
and basically remove
the call to "self halt". So, Ok.
It goes back to normal.
Now, if we call a method
that has not been defined.
For example, "self undefMethod".
If we save this piece of code,
we will see a new warning:
"Super and Self Messages sent
but not implemented"
and "Messages sent but not implemented".
Basically, it really does not understand
what this undefMethod is.
You can look at what those warnings
are by clicking on the question mark.
"Checks if messages sent to self
or super exist in the hierarchy"
and this "Checks for messages
that are sent,
but no class in the system
implements such a message".
Basically, it does not recognize
the undefMethod.
What you can do now... Let's just leave
this in the method to see.
What you can do now in your package is
right-click and go to Browse critiques.
If you click on that, you will have
a Critic Browser that will open
that basically lists all the rules
that Pharo defines
and runs them against your package.
There are lots of them.
For example, if we go to Bugs,
you have a lot of them.
You can read them and see what they are
or what they mean.
A thing that is really nice is
that if you know that this is a rule
that is wrong for your package,
you can simply mark it as wrong.
So, that is basically a false positive.
You can mark them as wrong
and then you can save these critiques.
If you save them:
"Do you want to save all false positive
and toDo?". Yes.
This will create a new class
in your package
which is called "ManifestMyCounter",
that basically
holds all the false positive
and things
that you just stated in the critiques,
and that you can later on version
and integrate in your continuous
development cycle.
In this video, we learned
how we can use the automated feedback
on the window under your code
and how we can use
the Critique Browser to version
and integrate in a wider continuous
development process
in order to certify that your code
still does not break the rules
when you push it.