-Hi everyone. In this video,
we are going to look
at how we can use the tool Metacello
to load external packages
inside your Pharo environment.
The package we are going to look at
is called "Containers-Stack".
It basically consists
of stack implementations
with push, size, top,
and pop variations.
A really simple stack implementation.
You can see in the paragraph Loading
that you will have a piece of code
that is calling Metacello
along with a baseline
and repository arguments.
We are going to look into the baseline
a bit later on.
But if we look at the repository, it is
basically this URL slightly modified.
Let's just try to copy this
into our Pharo environment.
Navigate to our Pharo environment,
System Browser open.
We are going to look for containers.
We have the definitions
of containers, rings.
If we go to Pharo,
Tools then Playground,
you can paste the code I just copied
and then, if we execute it with Cmd+D,
you can see
that it is loading everything,
and we can now see those 3 new packages.
Basically, we have the Containers-Stack
where there is the actual
implementation of the stack.
Then a test package which we can check
if it is green. It is, great.
And we have got
BaselineOfContainersStack.
This was what I was talking about.
Basically,
baselines are classes which only have
one method called baseline.
It will specify which packages every
package in your actual project will need
in order to work correctly.
Here, we can see that we have got a spec
package for the Containers-Stack-Tests
that requires the actual
Containers-Stack in order to work.
It is a real simple baseline,
but this will help you
specify how your project
will work altogether.
We can see, if we go back
to the GitHub page,
that "If you want to depend on it".
So, basically,
if you want to use Containers-Stack
in a bigger project,
you can use the spec baseline
Containers-Stack
with spec repositories.
So, this is something you have
to include in your baseline
in order to depend on this project here.
We learned how to use Metacello
in order to load GitHub repositories
with a baseline.
A baseline is something that specifies
what a project needs
in terms of dependencies
in order to load correctly.