In this video,
I’d like to show you that Nautilus
offers refactoring. What is
refactoring?
It’s an operation that transforms
code while
preserving its behaviour.
You have to note that historically
refactoring has been
been implemented for the first
time in Pharo’s ancestor,
and after that in all the
languages like Java.
As soon as 95, Smalltalk
had a refactoring tool
and Pharo’s one is inspired
by this tool.
So let’s open Nautilus to look
at the types
of refactoring proposed.
We will work on our class.
Refactoring is at several levels.
There is refactoring at the class
level, at the
method level and at the code
level, we’ve got
all those types of refactoring.
You can have refactoring at
the instance
variables level and at the class
variables level.
When a refactoring is very
useful it appears
at the highest level in the menus,
for you to
go faster, you don’t need to
click on class,
refactoring, Rename, it is here.
In the same way, for methods
refactoring, you will have all
those methods there,
with also Rename, as it is
an important refactoring
at this level.
Now if I choose another
piece of code, they are not
very complicated
in this class, we will have the
following refactorings
working at the method code level.
If I rename, if I do Rename on
the Counter class,
I call it Counter Class2, the
system says ok.
I do a Rename, all right.
It gives me feedback, I
don’t know exactly what this means
but no matter, I ignore it.
And here, I see that
where the Counter
Class was invoked it is
now Counter 2 instead.
This is typically a class rename
refactoring.
SO now, if I want to rename,
and this is a very
good example, let’s imagine I
want to rename the increment method.
I do Rename, and as I lack inspiration,
I will call it Increment2.
Here the system tells me:
“Be careful”
So I am careful.
“Be careful, you are about to rename
several (there are around 10
implementors in the
system), you are about to rename
them, do you really want to do this?
First, I don’t want to do it,
second I don’t
want neither to select or unselect.
So we could do it,
it enables to show that,
at the end, the programmer
is still in charge to
choose. I don’t want to do it.
However what I can do is saying:
“I am only working on
MyCounter package
and I don’t really the rest of
the system
to be modify automatically.
So I say to Nautilus: “I’d like
you
to open a browser on my package
only and
that all the operations refer
to that selection.
That’s what I do with
browse scoped.
That what you can also get
by pressing
the Scoped button,
that’s the same thing.
That’s a feature so interesting
that it has a
button. The difference between
those 2 worlds,
if you look at them, is
that here I have all my packages
and here I only have one package.
I could have several, I only
have one selection of these packages.
And now, if I want to modify
increment
I can say: “Rename”
as increment2
and it will do it only
locally on the package or on
the selection in the scoped browser.
I click on OK, and now we will
look at the tests.
My tests still work,
they are all green.
And I see that now all my
Increment have been renamed
as Increment2.
In this video we have seen that
Pharo
offers you a variety of operations,
selections and code manipulations,
with extra
restrictions on packages subsets
to control where changes will
be applied.
In Pharo, you also have
a tool that will enable to
rewrite code
automatically, I won’t expand
on it, I you really need it
you have to ask for it, there
is a specific
tool to do this kind of actions.
Now the last point I wanted
to show you
is that often you have operations
that are
proposed, generated.
You will apply them, the system
will propose to execute them
but it is not sure it will work,
it will be really appropriate.
What Pharo proposes is the
same as what Nautilus proposes,
it is what we call smart suggestions.
Smart suggestions are a tool
which knows
and propose you operations
based on the current selection.
For example, here it can propose
me to do
Extract method. It is not
very interesting in this
case, or an Inline method.
But it means that if I
selection for example the allocation,
I won’t have at all
the same operations available.
If I am on a class, it will
ask me to
browse the references,
to rename the class.
And you see that depending on
where the cursor is
I don’t have the same operations.