In this video, I’d like to show
you that Pharo
also offers the possiblity
to have an assistant that
checks your code quality,
it is called either
the Quality Assistant, or
Code Critics. It runs
automatically good practice rules
on your code.
Let’s have a look at it
more closely.
You’ve seen that each time you
browse a class,
you have this pop-up that
is displayed.
In fact, what happens is that
automatically,
while I’m browsing,
(let’s choose CubHelix
to see),you have
this little area here
where indications
are displayed. And when I go
on the package also.
As it is a little bit difficult
to find a
convincing example, we will
use our own code and
write ugly code in it, this way
you will see.
If I go into Counter, let’s imagine
for example that
I leave debugging code,
here the system tells me
automatically 2 things.
It says that there is debugging
code left
in the method.
What can I do ?
I can understand where does
this rule come from.
So I click on it, it tells me
to use
breakpoints, which is not
specially smart in production code.
It can tell me, I will automatically
solve this problem.
Let’s try, we will see.
It says to suppress this.
Ok, very good.
And as a consequence, I
don’t have this problem anymore.
You’ve seen that we do it
while I am
programming.
Finally, the system will react.
Now, there is another way to do it,
I can
open the Critic browser on
my package.
here it is a very small package.
Let’s make a mistake in order to
see it.
Here if I do "self halt"
or far example I do another
method,
I create an “increment3” method
and
I invoke a method which
doesn’t exist.
Let’s call it "foofoo".
So here it is red but let’s suppose
I haven’t
noticed it because of a
feverishness state…
I’m gonna use the Critic browser
on my code and here
the Critic browser
shows me the set of rules.
There is in fact quite a lot
rules
with explanations. If you have
this code there, in this
case you’d better use it
that way, if there is
an allocation inside.
There are several kinds of rules.
There are rules linked to
optimisation, rules
that can potentially identify
fixed bugs.
Rules that identify true.
If I go there, I see the code.
I can browse the definition
as we did before,
or I can transform it.
And the warning disappeared.
Now it is important to notice
that
all these rules are based
on heuristics.
This means that sometimes
you do things
that are not very good.
You know it and you
have to let it that way in
the system.
You can also say that this
is a false
positive. Let’s imagine
I have a “foofoo”
message and I know I want to
keep it, I can
specify that this rule is false
for this method.
I will write it.
Here it is in grey, what
does it mean?
It means that later I could
look at it
and say myself maybe this rule
was true and
it made sense to take another
look at it.
We can save the critics.
It means we save the rules results
and
as well the false positives.
When we write something was false,
we don’t want
the system to repeat it
constanltly
each time we run the rules.
So when I save the critics,
it will put them in a manifest.
Let’s look at it. Here there
is my manifest which will
be assigned a version
associated with the system.
You don’t need to see how it is coded
inside, we don’t care.
The Manifest enables to code
things,but no matter.
You don’t touch to this, this is the
code-critics that will use it
for the next executions.
And you have a manifest for each
package.
When you assign a version to
the code, you
also assign a version to your
manifests, and when you
run again your code-critics,
automatically it
will take into account
all the false positives and all
the meta-remarks you
put in it.
So what is really interesting
with those quality
rules is that Pharo integrates
them in a development process.
We will make sure that,
each time you commit your project,
there are
Jenkins servers
that will load and run
automatically those quality
rules to check that
your program really follows
those rules.