Hello, this video will explain
an important feature of Pharo,
the doesNotUnderstand hook.
You've no doubt already seen
a debugger window with this message.
Where does it come from
and what is it for?
Let's look at an example.
We have the object node1.
We'll send this object
the message coucou: stef.
From node1,
we follow the lookup method
back to the object's class.
We don't find the coucou method
in this class.
So, we go to the superclass,
but it's not there either.
The virtual system informs us
that it can't find a matching method,
so it reifies the message.
We discussed reification in the video
on introspection and reflection.
Reify means to represent
an implicit concept as an object.
Here, it's a message.
We create an object
to represent the message.
It's an instance of Message class.
The virtual system will resend a message
to the object node1.
It sends the doesNotUnderstand message,
passing the object as a parameter.
This is a new execution
of the lookup algorithm.
The system will not find the
doesNotUnderstand method in Node class.
So, it goes back
to search in the superclass.
It finds the method, abbreviated to DNU.
Now it can now execute the method.
DoesNotUnderstand is a message
that the virtual machine
sends for you to objects
when a message has failed.
All classes can redefine this method
to give it a specific behavior
when a message is not understood.
This method is an important tool
that allows us to build many features.
It's used in automatic delegation,
distributed programming, and so on.
Here we'll look at
some uses of doesNotUnderstand.
Suppose we want to redirect
all our messages to a different object.
In a simple delegation, I create
an object that stores the target,
where messages will be sent.
I redefine the doesNotUnderstand method.
It takes the object aMessage
as a parameter,
containing the failed message selector.
Then I can ask this message
to resend itself.
I use sendTo: self target,
which is the instance variable.
I resend the message to another object.
Be careful, this is a powerful function
that can interfere with
the legibility of the code.
As it's explained here.
The code will show
who ultimately receives the message.
It's very useful for constructing tools
and building advanced mechanisms.
Another example we'll look at
is LoggingProxy.
The basic idea here
is to create a minimal object
that contains few methods,
and to customize
its doesNotUnderstand: method.
Then we'll swap a domain object
with this proxy, or minimal object,
using "become."
First, we create a proxy object.
We give the proxy object a subject,
which is the object
we're going to replace,
or the target.
We add InvocationCount to increment
the counter with each message.
We put the counter in initialize at 0,
since it has received no messages.
Then we add the subject,
which is what will be replaced.
Now we redefine
the DNU method on this proxy.
Every time a new message
is not understood,
its reception appears on the Transcript,
and the counter is incremented.
Then we forward the message
to the subject.
Like before,
we redirect the message elsewhere.
For sendTo, as you see
in the Message class implementation,
we simply use the Perform method
with Arguments.
We already explained this
in an earlier course.
Let's look at an example.
How do we use this LoggingProxy?
We'll create an instance,
the Object point.
Then we'll use "become"
so that everything
that points to this point
will inadvertently
point to a LoggingProxy,
which we instantiate.
Now if we send messages
to the Object point,
noting that "become" is now
an instance of LoggingProxy,
every time we send it a message,
it will display in Transcript
and the counter will be incremented.
This is what we did
in doesNotUnderstand.
At the end,
the counter shows a value of 3.
There are limits
to the proxy's framework,
as seen in the last example.
For example, we can't capture
messages an object sends to itself.
That gets tricky.
We can't use "become" with classes,
as reflective models have limitations.
It's also risky when the proxy
and the object to be replaced
both understand the same message.
When I send the message to the proxy,
it will reply,
rather than capturing it with DNU
and transferring it
to the target object.
Pharo has other more powerful
proxy frameworks that trap everything,
but they're more complex
than this simple example.
Another example
of how to apply this technique
is to dynamically generate accessors,
or even methods.
Here I've redefined
the doesNotUnderstand method.
I see a message has been received,
so I test if I have the instance
variables that include the message.
If so, I generate a new method
using "compile,"
to define a new method for the class.
This will return
the value of the variable.
Here I'm generating
the variable's read-accessor.
If the message sent
does not match the name
of an instance variable,
I send a super doesNotUnderstand.
This enables us to load
read-accessors automatically,
depending on
if they've been called or not.
In conclusion,
we've seen how to use minimal objects.
They're not direct instances
of the Object class,
but of the proto Object class.
They can be the basis for proxies.
By redefining the doesNotUnderstand
method, we can capture
the existence of a failed message
and then redirect the message.
It's a powerful hook that provides
the basis of many tools in Pharo.
But you must be very careful
when you use it.
It's only to be used when necessary.
Don't put it in the domain code yet,
it's a highly advanced technique.