This video is a Redo for the MOOC.
Redo means do it yourself,
watch the video and do what is
shown step by step.
It is also an invitation to
look at how we program.
I won't follow a precise script,
I will try to do it,
but if I encounter bugs or
things like that, I'm gonna
handle them as I go along.
In this video, the idea
is to program a little
language that you can find
in role-playing games like
"Dungeons and Dragons".
For example,
for the ones who have this
expression, what
does this expression mean?
It means: you must throw 2
20-sided dice and 1 4-sided.
You'll see it can be a Pharo
expression.
So in this video we're going
to implement a class representing
a die and a class
representing a handful of dice.
So let's begin.
We begin with defining a package.
We call this package "Dice".
I don't really want to see
other things. So in this
video I won't code in the
debugger, you've seen it in another
video, I will
do it on a case-by-case
basis, in an opportunistic way.
Here I define the "Die" class
which
has a certain number of "faces".
I compile. I add a class comment.
For the moment, not much thing
because it is very very simple.
We are starting to enable our
object to be initialized.
I will do it like this.
I call for an initialization of
the super-class,
by default I assign 6 faces
to my die because it is
the most common die.
Now I'm starting to
develop a
tests class, to be sure that what
we do
doesn't break what has already
been done.
Tests classes are sub-classes of the
TestCase class.
We call it "DieTest".
I have my tests class.
One of the first tests to do,
you
don't have always to do it
like this, but
in any case I want to begin with
a test that works well.
As for the moment we don't have many
things, I say that initialization is ok.
This is also a way to show you
how you can test that you can
catch exceptions
or that exceptions mustn't
occur.
Here I am saying:
"Die new should not raise error".
What does it mean?
It means that when I execute this
bit of code "Die
new", no error must occur.
I'm gonna classify my test
and execute it.
It's green. All right.
So now, I'd like to define the
method that makes a die roll.
I know that in Pharo there must
be a method
called "at Random".
At Random, what does it do?
It enables to have... Ok...
So now I look at the implementation
to be sure
it's ok. AtRandom, what does it
do?
It returns an integer at random
from 1 to self, so it's perfect.
So I'm gonna define a new
method in Operations.
What will it do?
Roll. I say: "you return faces
atRandom".
So I write a test for this.
TestRolling. What do we do now?
We create a die.
d:= die
new
And now I write
"1000 timesRepeat".
What? "d roll".
And I want this to be
between 1 and 6.
"Between: and:", it's
ok. "Between 1 and 6".
It is not very good
because here we created
a test only for 6-sided dice,
we could have said
it works depending on the
number of sides of the die.
We will do it later.
So I compile.
I get an error. Here it is...
It is ok, I have my test.
Now it's time to save.
Here I have my "Dice"
package, I save it locally,
"Save".
I had created others before
to train a little so I
create a new one
"New version with
rolling and test". All right.
Ok, it is saved.
Now I'd like to change
the creation interface.
First we rearrange
categories. If we want to change
a little the creation
interface. We say:
"to create a die
use die faces".
On this expression you must see
that faces is a message sent to
the die class and not
to an instance of die class,
as it is the case
in the roll method or in others
methods coded until now.
I will do this for you to understand
when you
have to use and go to the class
level or not.
Let's begin by writing a test.
"betterInterface".
If I go on with the same logic,
"TestbetterCreationInterface",
Here I'd like to do something like
this for instance,
and this to be faces.
I will do it slowly.
I go there and I type
"instance creation", faces: , anInteger.
I could write it in a short way
but here
I do it in a calm way.
I create a die.
I write "self new", as
self here is the die class itself.
I tell: "create an instance".
And now with this instance I
use
an accessor to assign it the value
passed as an argument.
Obviously, I return the die
that has just been created.
When the code will be executed,
it won't work because
faces doesn't exist, so don't
worry.
You see that the test isn't ok,
but
it's normal, if I
execute this
for example, if I do debug to see...
And I click on Over, here it
says: "I don't know
the faces message."
Here we will do it calmly, I won't
do it in the debugger.
I say: "that's true, I have
to add an accessor
here. So I write
faces: anInteger.
And there I write : faces := anInteger.
And while I'm at it, I create
the read accessor.
I return this one.
And here my test is green.
So we save, "save"
"better die creation
method with tests".
All right.
Now we can start to
define what we want for
diceHandle. Basically if we
look, diceHandle,
how would we like to write it?
We would like to write
diceHandle new addDie.
So now we are going to create
a new die, "die faces 6, addDie".
"Die faces 10".
We start to write a
test class, this time.
So a new class which
inherits from TestCase.
All right. I have my new
tests class.
And I define a test.
The idea is to create a
handful and to
check there are the right dice
in it.
I write "testAdding",
I want to reuse my
code, there is no reason otherwise.
So I have my
handle; yourself , because I
want to
get the message receiver,
it is to say the handle
and not the argument that is here.
Now what should I do?
I write "self
assert h diceNumber
equals 2".
I compile. Obviously the system
says: "I don't
know the DiceHandle variable. Do
you want it
to be a class?"
Yes. It must be a class.
Here it will define it.
As I know that I have
to stop the dice anyway
I take this opportunity to
put an instance variable.
I compile all this.
Now it's red because "Add die"
hasn't been defined.
So we will do it.
Before doing this, it will
be nice to initialise
the handle, so we do it like this,
it will prevent
to have a bug later.
dice : = OrderedCollection new.
Recategorize.
And now, I must be able to
run my
test, which will crash.
Ok, very well.
I create Add die.
Adding.
It says: "You should implement
this method."
Yes, it makes sense.
I write "Dice add aDie".
Ok, very good.
My test won't still
work because I still don't
have defined the diceNumber
method, let's do it.
Yes, diceNumber,
we will create it, in
accessing this time.
And diceNumber,
what will it do?
It must return
dice size. I compile again,
proceed.
And my test should be green
so, the tests
are green and I save.
"With addDie and test".
We could improve the test because
here
it checks that we add 2 numbers,
I'd like
to check that when
we add twice the same die
we don't lose it.
I write
"TestAddingTwiceTheSame DieisOK".
Here what do I do?
I add 6 and 6 and I want to
get 2
I do this I run my test,
it's green, super.
Now, it will be nice to be able
to define what it is to do
add 2 dice. But before this,
let's do something.
If you look, what I don't like,
when I inspect this for example,
if I do "Inspect"
here, I don't see
the dice values and it's not
practical to debug.
In the debugger, we don't see this.
So before going on, I want
to improve
this. I'm going to add
a method
in the Printing protocol.
The "PrintOn" method
is defined on all the objects of
the system and
it will convert an object to a
textual representation and
pass a stream. We will only precise
the representation we want
inside it.
If I do this, I've done nothing
in fact.
If I do super PrintOn, in fact I've
done nothing.
Now I will do
"aStreamnextPut", so I will
put characters in the
stream, but what will I
put first?
I will write a parenthesis with a
space, maybe it
will be nicer, a parenthesis.
Then I will consider faces
and convert them
in numbers, in strings, and
concatenate all this
with a closing parenthesis.
If I do this... I closed the debugger,
so I open it again.
I have the debugger. Now
I have a 6-sided die
and a 10-sided die. So it is
much
nicer, you will see, if we
encounter bugs, it will help.
So here I didn't do anything special,
my tests are running.
I save again, it doesn't cost
much, "With printing".
We write "with die printOn".
All right. Now we create the
test, we won't
do it, we will go
directly there.
We select "add
protocol", "roll", "operations".
So,
there are several ways to define
this.
I propose you one, this is not
the nicest but
at least it is probably the
clearest for you.
There is a compact way, I could
do it in one line, but using
iterators
like "Injected to", here I'm
gonna use a loop.
So what do I do?
I take a value that I
initialize to zero.
Then I do a loop on all the dice,
and
for each loop step I get
a die, and what am
I going to do with this die?
I ask it to get a die roll
and to add the result to
my variable.
Nothing very special but at least
it is very very explicit.
Now if I do "Inspect" and there
"Roll", 5, it doesn't prove
it is working.
Let's try once more.
11. Ok, it's working.
We are gonna try to write
a test, there is
no reason, so we do
"Test", I want to see this one
and I call it rolling.
So how do we have to do to test
this?
It has to be between one and
the maximum of the number of dice.
So we will do this.
We
could define a method
doing this.
Let's create a method
defining the maximum.
"Operation maxValue".
What is maxValue ?
It is very close to this.
Here instead of doing roll,
I will ask for the faces.
Let's check. If I do
"Inspect", there
I do "maxValue", "16".
Yes, it's right 10 and 6.
So we write a test for
"maxValue". So I have this,
I do "maxValue equal
16".
So here you see, I could have
coded something
very dirty in my test, but
finally, it is better
to create a method in the class
and to use it.
So now, we can test the
roll method
works well. Let's do
"roll",
and say it must be comprised
between... "Roll between 1 and
h maxValue.
If I do this, ok it works.
This is not very statistical,
so here we could do
something like
1 000 timesRepeat.
Ok. And there,
we have our 1000 tests.
Now we save. All right.
We save once more.
"save" added maxValue
and roll with tests.
We've almost finished,
what we want to express now,
is
instead of having "die faces 6",
I'd like to have "1 D6".
And
what you see at the end is that
it means "send
the message 6 to a small integer".
So we go and look at the
integer class.
What we are going to do is
to define a class extension.
What is a class extension?
I'm gonna package my methods
with the same name as my package.
So you will see, what do I do?
I add a
protocol, I put *, it must
start with *dice which is
my package's name, automatically
this is put in grey, and
it means the method will be
packaged
at the same time as this package.
So let's do it.
Let's imagine we do...
What is D6?
A D6... I have to think
a little about it...
We first create a handle because
it could
be 2 D6 finally.
So "handle", we do
"diceHandle
new",
ok, so I have created my thing.
Now for each receiver,
I will do
"self", this is my integer,
"timesRepeat".
We will have really used a lot
the timesRepeat, it's rare.
"TimesRepeat handle addDie", of what?
Of "die faces". And there,
we know it's 6.
And indeed, it would maybe be
good to return the handle.
So does it work?
We're going to test like this and
we write a test.
But if I do 2 D6, Inspect,
look,
I do have 2 D6. So that's cool.
Let's write the test.
We will categorize those tests
after all.
We write "testNewSyntax".
Here for the moment we only have
D6, we will generalize later.
We want to do exactly the
same thing
than this, so we will have
an handle, let's say 2 D6.
And there, we do
"selfAssert".
What could we test?
That diceNumber equals 2
for instance. So you've noticed
sometimes I use
diceHandle, I could have also
used = 2 here.
In general, it is nicer to use
assert equal
because like this, when there is
an error, the system
says: "I've received this and
got this value instead of..."
If I write =, it will say:
"I've got a wrong expression."
Here for the final user, who is
yourself,
as a developer, it is better
to use
assert equals because it will
say: "I've received 3 whereas
I was expecting 2", for instance.
So here, I do this.
Ok, it works.
Could we have a smarter
version of this test?
For the moment, it suits us.
You see that now in
the package, I have an extension
called D6.
We will generalize this
with
"aNumberOfFaces"
So "aNumberOfFaces",
we put it there.
And we rewrite D6 because it would
be better.
We write D6 like this. We do
returns self D6.
We do all the other ones.
We do 4,
2. It's more a coin than a die,
but 2,
10 and 20.
You've understood the principle.
So let's run the tests, as we've
changed the implementation.
2 D6... it means it works.
So let's save.
What is there still to do?
In fact, we have still to be able
to add the handles.
What tests do I want?
For instance, I want to be sure
if I do
"addingHandles",
(I can use the new syntax,
so it's nice)
I want to test that if
I write 2 D20 + 3 D5
or 3 D6 instead (don't start to complicate
things). How much should I get ?
diceNumber should be equal to 5.
So here you see that we have to define
the + operator.
In Pharo + isn't an operator,
it's just a message.
So we define a message on the
DiceHandle class.
We write +.
So "aDiceHandle".
Now we can wonder if
we modify the receiver or
either if we use
a functional approach.
I prefer to use a functional approach
in which we create
a new handle.
So I'm gonna create a
new handle, I write
"handle self class new".
Here I avoided to write
diceHandle and later there
will be a lesson explaining why.
I prefer, it's closer.
In general you don't hard-code
the classes' name.
You will see it in week 7 or
something like this,
there is a complete explanation.
If I do "self
dice do", I
iterate on my dice
and I add them in handle.
So I do
"handle addDie each",
and I do the same...
Here I don't
need self and in fact I don't
know
the message, that's what it was
telling me, and
it makes me notice that, indeed,
I haven't defined it
and it hasn't worked for
"diceHandle", but
no matter, let's compile first
and we'll fix it later.
So here, what does it mean?
It means it lacks an accessor,
dice.
So we add dice here,
dice returns
the collection of my dice.
Now I'm gonna test, see if
my test is ok.
My test is ok, it's super, it
means I have
almost finished, I save,
"with handles
additions". Ok, all right.
It means now we can write
2 D4 and we
can do "Roll", and it returns
a number.
Now you are ready to play
"Dungeons and Dragons".
What you have to know:
we defined
our methods, we defined
our tests, we run
them, we extended a system
class,
the integer class, with extensions
linked to our
package, which will only be visible
when our package will be loaded.
We also overloaded operators,
but
in fact we only defined a new
+ message, because
in Pharo the addition is
just another message,
this enabled us to
express quite easily a nice DSL.
So now it's your turn to code!