In this video,
I’d like to show you that Spotter
offers categories to sort
your search results,
and how you can select them.
Let’s imagine I search for a package
containing the Spotter word.
Here, Spotter shows me I can
access to Spotter
via a menu, I can browse all
the classes
containing Spotter,
here it shows me I get
5/122, and there, #Package.
You see that each time
there is the
word #Menu, #Class,
#Package, #Implementer,
it’s what we call categories
in Spotter.
Now, if I want to select a
category in particular,
I start by typing the beginning
of the category, so P A.
There is only one beginning
with #pa, so #Package. And there,
it shows Spotter packages.
If I consider GT-Spotter and I
type enter, I go
on the Spotter package.