In this video, I'd
like to show you how
Nautilus enables to browse
inside
classes, and how to make more
detailed analyses.
Let's open Nautilus.
We select once more Parser class.
Now if I go there, I have
an item menu
called Analyze.
Analyze offers me
several queries on the system.
Here for example it will
let me know all the methods
referring to an instance variable,
all the methods
making assignments to instance
variables,
all the unreferenced
instance variables,
class variables.
Previously, we've seen there
were class references.
But let's have a look: if I
select instance variables, base,
I get all the NumberParser class
methods
accessing to base
in a way or another.
Here by assigning it, and there
by using it.
It is so useful that
this button does it.
If I do the same with base,
I can get the accesses to my
instance variables.