I’d like to show you
that with Spotter, you can
also restrict the search area.
That’s what we will see.
I call Spotter. Let’s imagine
I search for the examples,
I write “example”, and
I know that
I’m looking for the examples
defined with
a pragma or which methods
are tagged with a pragma.
Here, I see that there are 4
pragmas containing the word
"example": there is
"example", "exampleWidget",
"worldMenuExample" and
"gtExample". Here to be
more precise, I can see
"example", so all those
methods contain an “example”
tag, and I see "gtExample".
Let’s choose "gtExample".
Now I am going to
select all the methods containing
"gtExample".
Here, I see that there are pragmas
and methods with
"gtExample" in their name,
and that the ones I’m interested in.
So I’m gonna select them.
Now I have all these methods.
I can choose to say “No,
I only want to see those
which are in
Morph". And then I see all the
methods containing either
the Morph class, or the
morph method, and I can
see the code associated with
each method.