Hello. In this sequence
we'll be looking at Reflection,
the capacity for Introspection
in Pharo and why it's useful.
A reflective system,
reflection is divided
into 2 major families,
Introspection
is a program's ability
to observe its own state,
Intercession is a program's ability
to modify itself.
To modify its own state
or interpretation.
Reification is a concept that consists
of making explicit (objects) things
that are normally implicit.
For example, the execution stack
in Pharo is explicit,
but can be got as a classic object.
More classically, a class in Pharo
is a totally classic object.
In other languages,
classes aren't objects.
A reflective system, as I said,
has its own representation of itself.
It's capable of representing itself,
and it can act on this representation
to modify itself,
and when it modifies itself
it changes its state and representation.
We call it a "causal connection"
between its representation
and its state.
If we change the state,
the system representation changes
as well as the state of the system.
Why is this interesting?
It's interesting because we'll use
this introspection and intercession
to look inside objects.
I'm defining a collection,
which I make an "OrderedCollection"
then I'll use the Pharo Inspector,
which is a tool,
which can look inside this object.
It's an instance object
of the OrderedCollection class,
as we see here,
it has instance variables,
"first index", "last index",
we have the values of this
object's instance variables
so 1, 12 and then
an array of 12 elements, OK?
We might wonder how
this Inspector tool
is able to look inside objects.
How can it see
the internal state of objects?
It uses introspection methods
to look inside the objects,
There are lots of them,
defined as "objects".
So "instVarAt" allows us to see
an instance invariable
according to its number.
I'll see instance variable
number 1 of this object.
I can modify instance variable number 1
of this object by setting a new value,
or I can access an instance
variable by its name,
or change it by its name,
"instVarNamed put". OK?
Here are some examples.
Typically we create a point,
and then we do...
the point is 10@3
instVarNamed: 'x'.
I'll get the value of the instance
variable called 'x' of this point,
which gives me 10.
Then "instVarNamed: 'x' put:33"
I've changed the value of
the instance variable 'x' of this point.
It's gone from 10 to 33.
I've been able to change
the inner state of an object,
by using introspection and intercession,
particularly intercession,
"instVarNamed put". OK?
The main point is that
we've violated encapsulation.
An external object has modified
this object, without being internal,
so it violates encapsulation
but it's extremely useful
when building tools
and during development.
It's not to be used in the normal
code of an application,
but it's extremely powerful
for building generic tools,
typically code inspectors.
I'll give you another example
of introspection, the class method,
for getting the class of an object.
It's defined in "Object>>class".
I ask this string its class,
it gives me the class string,
this point what is its class,
the class point,
"Smalltalk class",
I can ask the class of the class class.
etcetera, then I add class class...
Basically, I can query the system
by sending the message "class"
to objects to discover their class.
There are many methods
for querying the system.
Here, I take "OrderedCollection"
and send it lots of query messages.
I'll get all of its superclasses,
all of its selectors,
the name of its instance variables,
all of the selectors,
all of its subclasses, etc...
And all of its lines of code.
All of this allows us to build
top level tools,
such as the navigation system here.
This navigation system lets us
show or browse the system.
For example,
I can see all the classes
that implement the method "#,".
Here we've a window that will open.
We'll see all the implementors of #,
so the class "AbstractFileReference"
implements the method "#,".
I've a list of all the classes
implemented by this method.
Another example,
we'd like to implement
a menu or a button.
By clicking on it, we want to send
a message to the object behind it,
according to the button's name,
for example.
How do I turn a string into a message
to send to an object?
I've an intercession method for that.
"Perform" defined under "object".
I pass it a symbol,
the name of a message to execute,
and it will send this message
to the object in question.
I've a 2nd kind of message,
"perform with".
I can give the name of the symbol,
the name of the method to execute,
and then pass a list of arguments.
An example, if I do "5 factorial"
sending a classic message,
and send the reflective message,
its "5 perform # factorial"
that's a symbol which means,
"Object 5, please execute
or receive the message factorial".
The normal lookup is applied
and these two forms are the same.
Here's another example.
Here we have a code inspector
"Ordered collection", we can see inside
the class "Ordered Collection".
This class contains attributes,
instance variables,
for example "methodDict".
In "methodDict" we see
that the class "OrderedCollection"
comes from "Behaviour"
so it has a "methodDict' here,
an instance of "MethodDictionary"
containing "CompiledMethod".
So we can see
this method dictionary contains
a compiled method here, etc...
another compiled method...
Lots of compiled methods.
We'll be able to ask each
of these compiled methods
for their source code.
If I do "self getSource"
I'll get the source code
of the compiled method.
But we can go further.
A compiled method can be asked
to execute itself directly
with the message,
"valueWithReceiver:arguments".
But watch out!
If I do that, there's no lookup.
Seeing as I already have
a compiled method,
it executes itself directly
without a message.
Here I'll ask the integer class
to get its compiled method "factorial",
which I get from the
class compiled method.
I send it the message,
"valueWithReceiver:arguments".
I pass it the arguments,
the receiver will be 5,
the arguments will be (),
because it's a unary message,
and we'll get the result.
It triggers execution of the
compiled method without lookup.
So to summarize,
reflection is extremely powerful.
We've seen it's something
that allows us to introspect
the whole system
because it represents it
in itself as an object,
but also to modify
the state of the system.
It lets us build tools
in a generic way in all objects.
So you can really talk to objects
with a protocol that's structurally
the same for all objects.
But watch out!
It violates encapsulation.
It isn't used in operational code,
but for tool building.
It facilitates the writing
of code inspectors as we saw,
and you can see how
it's implemented in Pharo.