In this video, I’d like
to show you more
advanced analysis you can do
on code with Nautilus.
So let’s open Nautilus.
We consider for instance
a simple class, NumberParser.
Now we look at what
we call Senders and
Implementors.
Often, we know someone
is fluent in Pharo when
he has understood how to
use Senders and Implementors
to find information.
So let’s have a look:
I consider a method,
I’d like to know what
calls this method:
what do I do?
I use Senders Of.
What will I get with Senders Of?
I get here only one method
which calls Senders Of,
it is called
ReadExponent and it calls
ExponentLetters.
It is an interesting information.
Now let’s imagine I go
in the public
protocol, I choose
NextInteger. I ask the Senders.
I will get this potential
Senders list.
In fact, these are all the places
that send the NextInteger message.
Here I see I am in the
NumberParser
class, and I call
Self.
As I use Self to do a call, it
will necessarily
be the method I have here
Now on the packages or the XML
class, it is not so
obvious because I don't necessarily
know, as Pharo
is a language with no types,
I don't know for sure
if this is the method concerned.
In fact, the system shows
that a message
with the same name has been sent.
In order to check this,
I can for instance
say that I'd like to know
what are the implementors,
how many times is
the method implemented in the
system.
To do this, I will select
Implementors Of.
Implementors Of. Ah bah
look, whereas in the other
case I only had one method, so it
was necessarily the one
that was called, here I have
several ones.
This method, NextInteger, is
defined
on NumberParser, but it is
also defined on XMLInteger.
XMLInteger is even defined on
two different
classes. So I see that these
methods, these calls are
message sends
calls and they will be resolved
and the methods selected.
You see that Sender and
Implementor are
very important.
With Implementor you will
see all the system's classes
implementing a method.
With Sender you will see
all the calls made to a method.
Senders are really very important
because
they enable you to look at
examples,
to find how a method is invoked.
Here I've selected a method
with no argument,
but if I had chosen a method with
an argument,
for instance Number,
NextNumberBase and I click
on Sender: what will it
show me? I have an argument,
and I see it is
the base.
Here it appears it is not
an argument,
it is just a call that has an
argument.
But in this test here,
I see that
if I instantiate
NumberParser on Stream,
and then I send it the message
NextNumberBase
and the argument 10.
It makes me understand how
I have to use the API.
It is so much used that there
are keyboard shortcuts.
Nautilus was first designed
so that you can
do all these operations
without touching the mouse.
Here notice that B means
browse.
So we will do Browse Sender,
N is for Sender's N.
Browse Implementor, M
is for Implementor.
If I select only "NextNumber"
for instance,
and I do Browse N, I will
get
NextNumber's Senders.
In the same way, if I select
I get them.
Now if I want to get the
Implementors, Browse M,
I get the Implementors.
In the same way about classes,
I'd like
to know what are the other system
classes using
NumberParser.
To know this,
I select Analyze,
I have Class
references. And I get all
the classes. I get all the methods
using...
Here I see they are mainly tests.
Look: in  ClassInteger, I call
the Parser.
Here, the tip to understand
is to remember the
keyboard shortcut,
Browse shift N, with a
capital letter because it is
the same as to
invoke a method, except here
we want
to invoke a class and a class
is bigger than
a method, so we have a capital
letter.