Hello.
Today we will review
the implementation of ifTrue:ifFalse:
If you've been attentive
and I'm sure you have,
you surely noticed
that when I suggested examples for Not,
I said you could implement
Not, Or and ifTrue:ifFalse:
But in the solution,
I never mentioned ifTrue:ifFalse:
We'll solve this problem now.
In effect, in Pharo,
conditions are messages.
Here's an example.
We have a weather class:
"Weather isRaining".
This means that if it rains...
If it's true, I'll take my umbrella.
If it's false, I'll take my sunglasses.
With ifTrue:ifFalse:
You see the two colons?
This means they're keyword messages.
The message ifTrue:ifFalse:
is a keyword message
and it's sent to a boolean instance.
In reality, it is heavily optimized
by the compiler and not really sent,
but conceptually speaking it is.
So if you want to redefine
the method ifTrue:
ifFalse:
You can do this in Pharo.
I'll explain the technique now.
The ifTrue:ifFalse:
method is so important
and we need it to go so fast,
that the function
is not actually invoked.
The compiler makes jumps inline instead.
But for the purpose of this class,
we'll see how it functions.
I want you
to propose an implementation.
You know about blocks.
You know what we did with
True and False,
and with Or and Not.
You can do it with ifTrue:ifFalse:
In sum, if my receiver is false,
I return 5.
And if my receiver is true,
I return 3.
Once again, we have objects,
messages and blocks.
It's a bit repetitive,
but that's the way it is.
You remember that brackets...
freeze the execution
of the expression they contain,
and that "value"
kicks the execution of a frozen code.
With this, and Not and Or,
you should be able
to implement your conditions.
Likewise, you should
be able to implement ifTrue:ifFalse:
I'll give you a few seconds to think.
How is it implemented?
In exactly the same manner
as Or and Not.
In the True class,
I have a method called
ifTrue: ifFalse: and two arguments.
One block for True
and one block for False.
What do I do?
When I'm in the True block,
I execute True.
And when I'm in the False class,
I have the same method
with the same two arguments,
but since I'm in the False class,
I execute the False block.
I have the booleans' implementation.
How does it work?
Like this.
When I send a message to my boolean,
which is in fact True,
I send ifTrue: do something True
or do something False.
Then I look up ifTrue:ifFalse:
in the True class,
It's right here.
It says to execute the True block,
so I do.
Now I send the message
"B is a boolean: False."
I send the message and look here.
I find ifTrue:ifFalse:
It says to execute the False block,
and that's what I do.
You cannot test this by putting
a breakpoint in ifTrue:ifFalse:
It's optimized
and the system won't accept it.
But what I do suggest you try,
is implement in the same manner:
ifFalse: or ifTrue:
ifTrue: a Block 1,
and ifFalse: A Block 2.
Then implement them.
Use a breakpoint and experiment.
So what have we shown
with this example?
We saw that sending a message
selects the right method.
Here we decided
to let the receiver decide its behavior.
And we saw that brackets
freeze computation,
and that "value"
forces the execution of a frozen code.