Hello. In this course,
we will go over
how Pharo execution works,
and what sorts of files are used
when and where.
Until now you've been using
.image,
.source and .change,
and it's probably not clear to you.
It works, but I'd like to explain
exactly what it does,
so you can avoid future mistakes
and better control your system.
In sum,
the Pharo execution model
is a virtual machine
that executes compiled code.
This virtual machine
is platform specific,
and VMs exist for different versions
of MacOS, Windows, Linux,
IOS, ARM and Android.
It's the same execution model
as for C# and Java.
In Pharo it's exactly the same.
We have what is called
multiple stage compilation.
This means that the code you program
is compiled to bytecode,
which is a set
of platform neutral instructions.
And the virtual machine transforms
bytecode to assembly code.
This is how Pharo works.
It's the same
in other object-oriented languages.
The virtual machine is the file.
Depending on your OS,
it's either .exe or .app with MAC.
They're virtual machines.
They can be executed
in two modes,
either from a command-line,
or in interactive mode
with a graphic interface.
For example, with Linux,
when you use Pharo on a server
you usually use command-line.
The virtual machine executes
compiled code
and generates on the fly assembly.
This compiled code
is packaged and stored in an image.
A memory snapshot.
This image represents a virtualization
system for Pharo objects.
We'll see that next.
The virtual machine needs
only the image to execute programs.
Because this is where code is compiled
and where the objects are.
In addition, we have 3 files.
Image, change and source.
I'll explain each of these files
and their role.
The .image file is a memory snapshot
that contains objects.
It contains simple objects
like points, strings, etc.
Everything we use.
But it also contains compiled methods
and namely compiled classes.
So each time you save your image,
all objects are saved to the disc.
Image really is a virtualization system
ahead of its time.
At startup,
you get back all the objects you saved.
Namely the program counter,
which will also be saved
and restored exactly
where it was before you saved it.
The important thing is that
you have an OS and a virtual machine,
and above the virtual machine,
you have this system,
which is a memory space
where your objects live
and which you can save
to your disc or not.
And it contains your compiled objects.
That's why I put "1s" and "0s."
In addition,
you have change files.
A change file
is a file that contain backups.
Everything you do in Pharo is logged
and entered into
a sort of large virtual tape,
which contains all
of your additions and modifications.
It's like Big Brother,
only it's for Pharo.
You can have fun with it and use it
to replay certain sequences.
It's a tape
that contains backups
of every action that modifies Pharo.
What happens is that, a change file
is associated to an image file.
What's the purpose of this?
When you define a new class,
the class code is not stored
in the image file,
it's stored in the change file.
So if you disassociate the two,
you could lose your code.
The program will keep executing,
but you might lose
the source code of your application.
If we look closely,
I have an image file that contains
my bytecode and compiled objects
in binary form,
and next to it, I have a change file
that contains a list of changes.
For example, here I added counter,
increase and decrease.
Likewise with other classes.
And we have tools that enable you
to replay these changes.
In Pharo, you can browse through
various versions of methods.
The tools that use different versions
of methods use .change.
I drew a dotted line around this couple
because it's very important
that .change and .image
remain synchronized.
Don't start editing text with Emacs
inside .change files.
You can do it,
but it's of no real interest.
You'll only break your .change file.
The image file will continue running
because it only uses .change
to show data in programming mode.
But I don't advise it.
Generally speaking,
images are handy to develop.
You're working
and someone interrupts you.
You save your image and take a break.
When you come back,
you're in exactly the same situation.
The entire state of your system
is stored on the disc.
You can come back 3 years later
and find exactly
the same state as 3 years ago.
But for a software engineer,
it's not good practice.
It's fine for development
and prototypes.
Please use
a Version Control System instead.
We have Monticello,
a versioning system written in Pharo,
and we have a backend for Git.
Save your code
in a Version Control System,
then use a continuous integration
server such as Jenkins or Travis
to construct your images
each time you startup.
People often confuse
these two things at first in Pharo.
Images are extremely practical
for development.
But when you want
more structured development
and greater control,
you must absolutely use
classical tools.
They work well.
There is a prototype mode,
but at some point you must save
to a Version Control System,
then you can access
all versions from your environment.
There are videos that explain
the counter class, for example.
There is a third file
I haven't talked about yet.
It's the source file.
A source file
is a sort of specific change file.
It contains all the textual definitions
of the system at .0.
For each new version of Pharo,
there is a new .change file,
and this .change file will contain
definitions for arrays, sets, etc.
All the methods that are defined
in the core libraries of Pharo.
Generally speaking,
you'll want to share this source file
and it's in read-only.
Change files are in write-mode
and there is one per image.
Let's take a look.
This is a snapshot of the system status
at the onset
of the new version of Pharo 4.0,
which corresponded to this universe.
Then we defined new classes.
I defined the Node class.
I created new objects in binary form,
and in the change file
associated with my image,
I added my new definitions,
which are written here.
Like I said,
this file is in read-only mode.
And this one is in write-mode.
Once again we can say that,
conceptually speaking,
the image and change files
function together.
I hope this has clarified the roles
of these 3 files.
What you need to know
is that we are putting together
a new change management system
so you can recover your files
more easily
or replay various versions
of your system.
In the future, there will
be better integration with Git,
and we will offer new ways
to produce images industrially.