-Hi. In this video,
we are going to have a look
at how you can basically customize
the startup of your Pharo image.
In order to do so, first we are going to
have a look at the StartupAction class.
So, StartupAction.
This is how it is used.
On startup, Pharo will call
a StartupPreference
in order to run
a specific series of startup actions.
In order to see this, what I am going
to do is to plug in StartupAction.
In order to find them, you go to your
Pharo environment, System, Startup,
Version Preferences folder.
And from there,
you select Create file
and you name your file "startup.st".
Press OK.
For now, what I will do is copy a piece
of code that should remove the logo.
You can see that basically it is
consisting of a StartupPreferencesLoader
that will execute
a series of startup actions.
This one is named "Logo" and you can
plug any piece of code you want.
So, they are simply
"showDesktopLogo: false".
I will remove this Pharo logo
in the background. I will save this.
You can quit this.
Now juste save and quit.
Go back to our Pharo launcher,
double click on your image,
and you can see
that the logo has disappeared.
You can plug in any code you want.
You might log your GitHub credentials
for example
or if you want to change the color
to some colors you like better.
You can do what you want.
This is how it is done.
If we want to revert it,
what we will have to do
is to go back to System. I can change
it there by going to startup.st.
For example, if we would like the logo
to come back, we set it to "true".
You do not have to close
and reopen your image.
You can simply go to Run startup script.
And our logo is back again.