In this session,
I’d like to show you how
to use the debugger to program
differently.
We will implement again
the counter application
but in a different way, with a
development flow more interactive.
First I will create
a new package with Counter,
as previously.
I will also filter to have
less elements.
In MyCounter, I first
define
a test, a test class.
Test classes inherit from TestCase.
I will call it Counter Test.
I will compile. I do it once
more in the menu and then
I do it with the comments.
It has created a test class.
In my test class, I write
a test method.
The test methods begin with test.
What do I do?
As previously, I define a local
variable. In
this local variable
I put an
object from the Counter class.
I initialise the Counter value
and
check that the Counter
has the right value.
I compile.
Now the system tells me:
“Warning! I don’t know
what Counter is.” It was already
indicated
with the italics here.
It proposes: “Do you want to define
a new class?
A new global or a class variable?
Here it is a new class.
It offers the class definition.
I say: “ok, it’s correct, it’s
in the right package, it inherits
from object, all right, do it.”
So it creates an empty class.
Now we are going to arrange this.
I can see that my Counter class
is empty.
If I execute my test, it is red.
Why is it red?
Because I have an error.
So how should I read this message?
Let’s take 2 minutes to do it.
The system says: “a Count message
has been sent to
an instance of the Counter class
and the corresponding
method wasn’t found.”
I’m going to look…
I open the debugger.
The debugger displays the execution
stack, so I can
see that a message hasn’t been
understood.
And there it shows where the
message has been invoked.
I see that if I go there,
I can see the
system variables. If I look at C,
I can access
to the temporary C variable, which
is valued a Counter.
Anyway, if I write C class
for instance,
self class, it says it is
the Counter class.
This is obvious. For the moment,
in my class, I don’t have any
method. I will ask the system
to create one for me.
I do Create.
It proposes the classes.
I choose Counter class.
Can you create this?
Yes, in Accessing.
And finally what did he do?
It compiled automatically
a method with the right signature.
For the method body, it doesn’t
know what to do,
so it uses
ShouldBeImplemented. What does it do?
It raises an exception at
the execution and the system
execute again the method.
Now there is a new error and
I have to
implement the method body.
I know Count.
What am I going to do?
I want to assign this value to
an
instance variable. So here
it’s red, because for the moment
my class doesn’t have this instance.
I compile.
The system proposes:
“Do you want a temporary variable
or an instance variable?”
I want an instance variable.
So I do this. If I look in my
class, I do have
a Count instance variable which
was created and
the method, the Setter, which
will set the value.
Once I’ve done this, I can tell
the debugger
to continue, Proceed means continue
the execution
as if nothing happened.
What happens?
There is still an error.
The system still says that
there is an instance
of Counter class which received
the count message and that
it hasn’t found the appropriate
method. This is normal because
C does have 7
in its Counter, in its count variable,
however
the count method doesn’t exist.
I’m gonna create it.
I will do Create. In which class?
Still the Counter class, in
the accessing protocol,
because it’s an accessor.
And there you
see that the system is smarter.
It noticed that there was an
instance variable named
count, and it wants to define a
method named count,
so let’s propose it an accessor.
That’s what I wanted.
So now I can Proceed.
What do I see?
My test is green. I have a test
green and
2 methods have been created
in my class.
Now I will do the same
for increment.
In fact, I am
specifying what the method
has to do
and checking that it does do it.
So there I must have 9,
I compile, I execute.
And the system tells me that
it doesn’t know the increment method.
Yes, it’s normal. I do Create,
here in operation.
If I look at increment,
I can do count.
= count + 1. I compile.
Proceed. I do have my test.
While I’m at it, I create decrement.
The idea is for you to do it,
to practice it.
So here it will be 5.
I define my test.
I create my method.
OK. So now you know,
count: = count,
I compile in the debugger.
I click on Proceed. And my
tests are green.
Now my class has 2 operations:
increment and decrement.
It’s time to save,
for example.
I’m going to save like I’ve
shown you before.
I click on Save, I save and
here I write "with
accessors and decrement
increment covered by green tests".
So here it is! I’ve saved that.
Allright.
The important thing to remember
in this session is that
the debugger gives access to
the object’s
state, it places you in the
right call context and
enables you to use the call context
to have all the necessary
information to write
your code.
And this is really very,
very powerful.