hello, I’d like to show you
how to use
the Finder to find information.
The Finder is a tool you will
find in
the Tools menu, here Finder.
Let’s imagine I want to look for
a method
called match.
I write its name, match.
qui s'appelle match.
Here I choose Selectors.
Now I see all methods
containing
the word match, with the code
here.
As I set up big fonts,
we wil
resize a little bit.
You see that when there is a
little
triangle, it means the method
is defined over several classes,
and I can read that kind of thing.
So that was for methods, and
there is quite a lot.
You can look for things
but that’s not ideal.
Now we can search for
classes containing match,
here we see all our classes.
The best way is to unbrowse
using the code browser.
Now there a far better way.
Often we know what we are
looking for
but we don’t know how to express
it.
So here, I know that I’d
like to know if there
is a method matching ab,
abcd, for instance, I write
ab*abcd
and if something matches it returns
true.
And I choose Examples,
and I get all
the methods returning True.
I’m going to explain what we
see.
Here I see that superior
works as well.
Ah, match seems interesting.
The system shows me all
the classes defining
the match method, but
in particular the one with the
little star is the one
which method has returned true.
So now, we can try other examples.
For example, given 11, 2
what methods returns 5. Here
I will have
// and I see what has
returned true, it’s defined
on Integer, so it is
this method or on aNumber
which is this method there.
So I do the same, in the same way:
Now I want 5.5.
Then I only get Diviser.
So it’s very useful.
There another way to do it:
you can look for
all the Pragmas, Pragmas
are the annotations
in the system. So if I
look what is an
annotation, for instance it is
this.
Here it is, I have annotated
my method with a pragma named
Menu, and the system can
make queries on it
to build menus.
Here by typing Menu, and
selecting Pragma,
I can access to all the system’s
pragmas containing the menu
word.
So here, we see that there are 2
for instance, 2 pragmas.
The worldMenu, the one which is
displayed
when you are here, is defined
by the Pragma menu.
You see worldMenu.
The screenShotCommand
for example. HelpOn.
You see all these menus.
So know, with the Finder we
can also
look for methods
containing the “Menu” string,
wherever they are.
I’m gonna do it: it takes a little time.
What happens is that the system
scans
really all the body of all
the methods, there are
80 000 in Pharo, or a little
bit more, and it displays the result.
So here, it’s really a textual
search.
What’s interesting sometimes,
when you see
a menu or something graphical
you can find it back.
So here, you have all the
methods containing the
Menu word, in their names
as well as
elsewhere, here or there.