In this video I would like
to show you
some simple elements of Nautilus.
I will show you
more complex elements
in following videos
related to the class browser.
Nautilus is what will enable you
to browse in the code.
I open it. What do we have?
You have all Pharo packages.
Let’s consider for example
AST-Core which is a package
used by the compiler to parse code
and represent code.
I have the AST-Core package.
I will have the classes
contained in the AST-Core package
and we can see for
instance that there is inheritance
here, RBAssignmentToken
inherits from RBToken.
Now, for instance, if I click on
NumberParser,
here you have
the NumberParser class.
Here, I can see its comment.
And there I see the protocols.
The protocols are conceptual
groups of methods.
If I click on “all”, I can see
all the methods
of this class, otherwise
I can select
some protocols giving me
a more precise piece of
information as, for instance,
initalize-release.
It means that it is the method
that will initialise the Parser.
Here you have all the methods
linked to the way you
parse a number.
I can see that this one is
public whereas
these ones are private,
indicating I won’t
have to call them from
the outside in a general way.
Now if I am here, I will see the
method’s code.