-Hello, everyone.
In this video, we are going
to look at syntax highlighting
and how it can help you
have direct feedback from the system
on the code you are writing.
For example,
if we begin by writing a capitalized C,
we can see that it is in italics.
That means that this prefix
is recognized by the system
to be the beginning
of an existing class name.
If we write "Color",
we can see that this word
is no longer in italics,
it has been recognized by the system
as being an existing class.
But what happens if we write "Colox".
This is red and this means
that it is not recognized by the system,
either because you have not installed
the correct package
or simply because it is the wrong syntax.
Right here, it is the wrong syntax.
If we go back to "Color",
and then we begin writing
a method name,
for example "ne".
This is in italics,
so that means the same thing
as for the class name,
that this beginning is recognized
by the system
but now if we write for example "nexx".
This is red,
this is not recognized by the system,
but if instead, we write "new",
this name is no longer italicized
so that means this method
is recognized by the system
according to this class.
"Color new" is something
that will potentially work
or at least is recognized by the system.
These were some quick tips
on how to get instant feedback
on the code you are writing
in a syntaxic way.
This will not ensure
that your code is always working,
but it means it is still recognized
by the system.