"Selecting Expressions"
Quentin Ducasse.
-Hello, everyone.
So, in this video, we are looking
at how we can highlight
and execute different expressions.
Right here,
we have a three-line expression.
What we are going to do is to click
and drag to highlight the first line,
then right-click and print it.
So, this is 1 000 factorial.
We can also double-click
at the end of the 1st line,
this will select the whole line.
Now, we can right-click
and print it again,
this is still 1 000 factorial.
If we look at the two-line expression,
what we can do is click and drag
to highlight the two lines,
right-click and print it.
This is 1 000 factorial
divided by 999 factorial.
This is 1 000, which is correct.
And for the three-line expression,
we can put the cursor at the end
and simply double-click,
this will select the whole expression.
From now on,
we can right-click and print.
These are some quick tips to select
and execute your expressions
and you can basically do this
in every Playground
or any Pharo environment.