"ProfStef"
Quentin Ducasse.
-Hello, everyone.
In this lesson, we are going to look
at the tool named ProfStef.
Basically, to launch it,
all you have to do is to write
"ProfStef go" in a Playground
and just highlight it
and do it.
This opens the tool.
There is some presentation.
Basically, this tool is there
to help you learn Pharo by yourself.
What you can do is,
for each lesson,
you can see here
that there are 29 lessons,
you will have some explanation,
then a "ProfStef next"
to access the next lesson.
What we can do is highlight it,
right click it and do it
to go to the next lesson.
So, once again,
you have some explanations.
These are explanations
on the "Do it" command.
What we can do, for example,
is select the "GTPlayground open",
right-click and do it.
This opens a Playground.
What we can do next
is do it to the next lesson
with "ProfStef next".
Do it.
This is an explanation
of the "Print it" command.
You can highlight, right-click
and print it this time
so it shows a 3.
We can do the same thing
with other expressions.
I will let you try those by yourself.
Let's go to the next lesson, do it.
And these are some explanations
of the "Inspect it" command, so this one.
Basically, if we highlight the "1/2",
it opens the Inspector on a fraction,
so half.
Basically, the flow of this tool
is to have some explanation.
Try it yourself
and then, inspect and browse
all the different commands Pharo offers.
I would really encourage you
to look at this tool
and try commands,
maybe do the 29 lessons
if you are motivated.