-Hello, everyone.
In this part 7 of the redo
and the last part,
we will look at the history
that the tool Iceberg will use
to save our changes
and commit them somewhere.
We will generate
the history of these changes
so let's go into the Iceberg tool.
We can go to our repository MyCounter,
right-click and go to Repository.
There we have a history
of the commits we did.
For example, the initial commit,
the time I added "increment2"
to show you the Iceberg way
to commit things,
then the initialization methods
and then printOn.
So, we can also see a difference
between these commits and HEAD,
which is the commit we are writing
right now in this image.
For example, here,
since the first commit,
we added "increment2",
"initialize",
started at the "printOn" method
and some test methods.
We can look at the difference
between these commits
and the commit before it.
Between "added 'increment2'"
and "initialization methods",
we can see that we added
the initialization methods.
We can have a good insight
of how our project development went.
And another interesting thing is that,
imagine that we do not need
the "printOn" or initialization methods
or they were wrong,
we can just go back
to this commit right here
by right-clicking and using Checkout.
This will show us the changes
that happened to the image.
This will remove "printOn"
and the initialization methods
and tests we made.
Press "Checkout" and if we look
at the System Browser here,
we can see that the "printOn"
and initialization methods
have just disappeared.
It is a good way for you
to come back to your code
if you made a choice that was not right
or if you feel
like there is another solution.
Iceberg can handle that for you.
So, this video was about
how to use Iceberg
to get a more insightful look
in your own project development
and how you might do things differently
by going back to a previous commit.