-If we are coming back
from the last part,
with the methods we defined,
the tests and everything,
now is a good time to save your image
and that is what we have done.
But how to save everything locally?
We can see there
that there is a small star on our package.
This means that it is not saved anywhere
except from within our image.
We can just use a tool called Iceberg
that will use version control
on your package.
For example, here, we can add a package,
then go to a new repository
that we will call "MyCounter".
The source directory will be "src".
Then, we can just press OK.
So, MyCounter is there,
but then, if we double-click on it,
we can see that there is nothing in it
but we can add a package.
So, we will add our package "MyCounter".
Okay, "MyCounter". Add.
"Uncommitted changes."
If you are familiar with Git,
it is using the exact same way
but locally.
Right now, we can do Commit.
These are all the things we added
to our package MyCounter
plus some internal files,
.project, .properties.
We can write a comment
for our commit, for example...
"Initial commit of a Counter
(increment
and decrement methods tested)".
And let's just commit.
Okay.
There we have a package
that has been saved.
Now, if we make some changes,
for example imagine
that we want to add another increment
called "increment2" that will add 2.
We can save this.
The method has been created.
Now, if we want
to save these changes in our package,
you can see that,
if we go back to our "MyCounter" package
from within Iceberg,
it has some uncommitted changes.
So, let's just commit.
We can see
that "increment2" has been added
and we can just write "Add increment2"
and commit.
This is our package
that is now up-to-date.
This is a good way to save a version,
a history, of what you are doing
as well as saving your package somewhere.