-Hello, everyone.
In this video, we will be looking
at how to create a test class
and some tests within it.
In the last part, we tried to see
if our accessors were working correctly.
Right now, we want to replicate
this behavior within a test.
In order to do that,
let's just go to the counter class
and create "CounterTest",
that will be a subclass
not of objects but of test cases.
And we will not need
the "count" instance variable.
Now we can press Cmd+S.
The CounterTest has appeared.
You can see that there is a grey button
on the left side.
This grey button can be used
to run over tests within the class.
Right now, there are no tests
so it is not doing much.
But we will just create one
that we will call :
"testCounterisSetAndRead".
Let's just copy and paste
the code right here
and on the last line,
so the last expression,
we will not simply output
the value of an instance variable
but run it against 7
and see if it is correct.
In order to do so,
we can just write "self assert",
then "c count"
and we want to run this
against "equals 7".
This will try "c count"
and see if it is equal to 7,
which is what would set it up to,
so it should work.
Let's press Cmd+S.
Our method is created
and we can see that,
the same way there is a grey button
at the side of the name of the class,
there is a grey button there,
so this will run the test
for this method.
If we click on it, we can see
that it ran and it passed.
If we click on this button there,
it will run all tests
from within the class.
It will only run one for now.
When your tests are green,
it is a good time to save your image.
We can go to the menu, Pharo, Save.
Now, let's create another test
but with another mindset.
Let's try to do
some test-driven development.
What that means is
that we will write the test first,
and implement the method
it needs to be green.
We will just try
to make a test increment.
We will set the counter to 4,
then increment twice
so we can do with a semicolon.
"Increment; Increment".
And we want it to be equal to 4
and let's put this one too.
Okay.
This should add 2 to the counter.
Let's compile it.
We can see that the method has appeared.
But if we click on the button there,
it should fail because we did not define
the increment method,
so let's click on it.
Yes. "Instance of counter
did not understand increment".
That's right, we have to define it,
so let's go back to the counter class.
Let's go here
and create a new method
called "Increment"
that we want to add 1 to the count.
Capitalize that.
"Count + 1".
Let's compile it, Cmd+S,
and you can see that the button is now
on the left of the name of the method,
first because the system knows
that there is a test
called "testincrement"
that is linked to this method.
We can just click on this one
and now, it's green.
If you go to our CounterTest
and press the button,
it is now running two tests
and the two have passed,
so it is a good time
to save our image once again.
Save.
The same way we defined increments,
we will go and define a test decrement.
It will run the same method.
"Decrement; Decrement",
but now we want the count to be 0
because we subtract 1 twice.
If we compile, Cmd+S,
the method appears
and if we run it,
it should fail and it is failing
because it does not understand
"decrement"
because we did not define it,
so it is perfectly normal.
Let's just go back to the counter class
and define "decrement"
so it should subtract 1 this time.
Once again,
it recognizes that there is a test
associated to this method
with the button to the left.
We can just click on this one,
it is green,
and now, if we click on the CounterTest,
it just runs all the tests
from within it.
We can see 3 tests have been run,
3 passed.
It is a good time to save the image.
In this video,
we learned how to create a class test
and how to define some methods.
Once again, test-driven development
is encouraged from within Pharo
as it is really simple to write tests
and you will see in the next week
how it is even easier to define methods
such as the methods decrement
and increment that we just wrote.