-Hello, so we are in part 3 of the redo
and this is more to precise
something that might have caught
your attention in the last part
which is method creation.
So, I often just...
overwrite the code and the text
of a previous method.
For example, here,
if I want to create a decrement 2,
I will simply go to Decrement
and rename it to "decrement2 count -2".
You can see that we are modifying
the code of "decrement".
You can see there that we are
in the tab Decrement with a small star,
meaning that we have not saved yet.
It should overwrite
the decrement method, right?
No, because when we save,
it will look at the name of the method
we just created
and if it changed
from the initial place we were in.
For example, here,
we are in Decrement
but the method we created
is "decrement2"
so it created a new method.
Same thing if we go there
and write "increment12",
that will add 12,
we are modifying the increment method.
There is this little star.
But as soon as we compile and save,
pressing Cmd+S,
this will create a new method
because the name has changed.
However, if we go to the increment,
now we want our basic increment method
to increment by 2,
which we do by simply changing
the "+1" to "+2",
and if we save,
the name is the same.
So, no new method has been added
but the increment method has changed.
Another thing is that there are no ways
to add a method from the menu
but there is a way to remove the methods.
We can just remove "decrement2" there.
This was just a clarification
on how to create and remove methods,
which might have troubled you.