"Advanced Spotter actions"
Quentin Ducasse.
-Hi. In this video, we are going to have
another look at the Spotter.
The Spotter can be accessed
either by going to Tools, then Spotter
or hitting Shift+Enter.
From within the Spotter, you can have
access to the menu, the different tools,
anything, but you can look for,
for example, class Point.
If I go over to Point and press Enter,
it will open the system browser
on the correct class and package.
But another thing you can do is,
if I go back to Point,
if I now would like
to dive into this class,
I can press the blue arrow.
Another thing I can do
is toggle the preview,
so pressing Cmd+P
or clicking on this gray arrow.
Cmd+P will toggle
the preview on this browser.
If I press this blue arrow
or press Cmd+Right,
Cmd+Right
will dive into the Point class.
I have different categories: Instance
methods, Super instance methods,
Class methods. I can look into them
by using "#instance", for example.
I will only have the Instance methods
or the Instance variables.
If I want to dive
into this method there,
I can just press Cmd+Right, or I can
dive into all the Instance methods
using Cmd+Shift+Right.
This will bring me to all the Instance
methods, reflectedAbout.
I have a preview on the right.
And if I am not interested
in all of these methods,
I can simply press Cmd and go back
on the left to go back to the beginning.
So, Point, Spotter, and I am back here.
Now, another thing
that is nice with the Spotter
is that if I write something
to the Playground, for example,
if I write "Date today". I print it
and we are the 10th of May 2020.
If I shut this window, now what I can do
is go back to the Spotter, Shift+Enter,
and you can see the history there.
We can go by scrolling,
but if I write "#Playground", you can
see there #Playground named pages,
#Playground cached pages.
So, for example, here,
we can press Enter
on this #Playground cached pages,
and it will open a Playground with
the last piece of code that was written.
So, it can help you if you forgot
what you had in your Playground
before closing it.
It can help you handle it.
Finally, if you are
from within the Spotter,
you can go into your file system
by using "./".
Right there, we are in the file system
and I will enter any of the directories
or mounted shells.
So, I will just type "#files".
Those are all the files around my image.
You can see that there is my image here,
"W5-LiveA.image", and we can go
over to the jpg, for example.
This will open the image.
Another thing that we can do is...
If I go back to "#files",
there is a zip document
and I can go into it
by pressing Cmd+Right.
This will make me go into it, see it.
I can see there is another jpg.
You can see that there is a text file
that I can get a preview from.
I can open the jpg
by simply pressing Enter.
The Spotter can really help you explore
both the internal system of Pharo
and the external system around it
if you need to access
some external documents.
I really encourage you to use it.
It is much easier
if you learn the shortcuts.
Cmd+Right to dive into,
toggle the preview,
or Cmd+Left to come back.