-Hi. In this video, we are going to have
another look at the Inspector,
and especially
how it can create the specific tabs
that we have seen in the last
presentation of the Inspector.
I will reuse the example that we defined
with the other dictionary,
Time, Date, Morph.
And if we look back at the date,
we can see that the time calendar
holding the calendar morph
is actually defined
if we use a tool called Finder.
Since the Inspector
is called the gtInspector,
we will look for gtInspector
in the Pragmas.
You can see this pragma called
"gtInspectorPresentationOrder".
If I double click on this one,
it will open the different senders
of his pragma,
and if I look for a date,
we can see that it is called,
within gtInspector, PreviewIn.
If I click on this,
you can see that there is the creation
of a composite morph
with a title "Calendar",
and using the morph "CalendarMorph".
This is how this tab is defined there.
We have got the Calendar title
and the CalendarMorph under it.
Now, if we look at other objects such as
"Morph new Inspect" and press Cmd+D.
This time, we have got a tab Morph
that depicts the actual morph,
and you can see on the right
some actions.
"Export as PNG" or "Delete".
We will try to find those there
by searching for Morph.
You can see that we have got
gtInspectorMorphIn,
and if we look into his code,
we can see that we have got
the same composite morph with a title,
and the display of his image,
and error handling
if it cannot draw the actual morph.
Then, the two buttons
that can be found there,
"Export as PNG" and "Delete",
that are defined underneath.
The last one we are going to look at
is a compiled method.
We will look at "Point>>#degrees"
and press Cmd+I to inspect it.
You can see that this one
has several tabs.
It has Bytecode, basically
all the instructions sent to the machine.
So, send the instruction ">=",
"jumpFalse", "pushConstant".
The Source. This is the actual
source code of the method.
The intermediate representation,
and an abstract syntax tree.
Those are extremely interesting.
What we can do, if I extend this a bit,
we can go to Raw,
open another view of a same object,
go to Bytecode on this one,
go to Source on this one.
And a nice thing, if I click on,
for example, this instruction,
"pushConstant: 0", it will highlight
the corresponding piece of source code.
So, this is extremely nice
for developers of a compiler
or if you are simply interested
in how the bytecode
is translated into the source code
and vice versa.
This is interesting and we will look
at how it is implemented.
It is implemented under CompiledCode.
It is right there.
You can see that we have got
the gtInspectorAST
that is implementing the AST tab.
The Bytecode tab is implemented there.
The Bytes, Header,
Ir, Pragmas and so on.
Everything is implemented there
using the gtInspector presentation order.
This video was there
to show you that you can find
how the tabs are implemented
and that the Inspector
is really interesting
to display a particular view
of the objects that you find.