Here I want to show you
how to load
packages deployed by other
people.
In Pharo, there is what we call
the Catalog Browser.
We're gonna open the Catalog Browser.
Here it will look on the Internet
and get the
catalog metadata,
and show us all the
packages deployed by people
that you can deploy too.
In fact, what happens is that
when you deploy a
package in a particular repository,
it will be
available in the catalog.
Now
let's imagine I'm looking for
XML, I will get all these
Parsers, here I have tags.
I see that XMLParser
works for Pharo 5, I could have
also searched for XHTML
validation, and I would have get it.
I click on it,
I have a little document.
I can install the new version
and
create a group if I want to or
only install the
stable release, or
change the configuration.
The configuration is the map managing
the dependencies between packages.
We install the stable
configuration.
It will take a little time.
Here it will get the packages on
distributed repository
and load everything in memory.
I launch my tests because there
is no reason otherwise.
I want to know if what that package
does makes sense.
I go there. I select all.
I click on Run Selected.
I have 2 187 tests which are
green, so it must work.