I'd like to show you how
we load code in Pharo.
I go on Safari to see.
I want to load the Counter
which has been saved in the
Pharo MOOC project, on Smalltalk Hub.
Here it shows the repository,
I copy it.
I go there. I do
Monticello Browser +Repository Http.
And I paste the definition.
Here, I click on OK. And now
what will the system show?
It will show "Yes, there's a
version - here unfortunately
there is only one -
one version of Pharo Counter."
I can do a merge which will
make a Diff between
what will be loaded and
what is in the image.
Here, there are only additions,
but if there were
modifications of existing
methods it will
show them and it will make
an interactive Diff.
I can also do a Load,
with this it will overwrite
the things that are in the image.
MyCounter, there was only this,
so I can do Load and here it is.
Now I have loaded my code,
I do
Counter.
If I go in Counter, my tests
are green, I can
begin to work.