Hello. Welcome to the fourth sequence
on inheritance and lookup.
We will now learn what happens when
the algorithm does not find a method.
As you will see,
the class codes
can add processing in this case,
to handle the fact
that a lookup message
was not understood.
I'll review message-sending briefly:
The "area" message is sent
to ColoredRectangle.
First, the algorithm looks up
the method matching the message.
It starts by searching for the method
in the receiver's class:
If it finds "area" in ColoredRectangle,
it executes it.
But "area" is not there,
so the algorithm searches the superclass
In "Rectangle," it finds "area."
The method is executed on the receiver.
What happens in the total absence
of an "area" method?
What if the lookup fails?
Here is an example: a "coucou" message
is sent to Object Node 1.
"Coucou" cannot be found
in the hierarchy.
The "coucou" message is sent to Node 1.
The algorithm fails to find "coucou"
in "Node."
Next, the algorithm searches
"Object." No "coucou"
At that point,
the Pharo virtual machine
sends a "does not understand" message
to the receiver - Node 1.
DNU = Does Not Understand.
It transfers the initial message
as a parameter.
This is the parameter: "coucou stef."
If I go through it again step by step,
"Coucou" is sent to Node 1.
A match is sought in the class,
then in the superclass.
"Coucou" is not there, so the message
"does not understand" is resent
to Object Node 1.
The algorithm looks up the method
"does not understand."
in Node 1 class.
Not finding a match there, the algorithm
searches the superclass.
It is located there.
A "does not understand" method
is found in Object and executed.
That means
in all the subclasses of Object,
"does not understand"
can be implemented
to trigger a specific behavior
when an object, instance, or class
does not understand a message.
This slide shows the details,
step by step.
"Does not understand" is a message
like any other.
Therefore, you can implement
a "DNU" method to be executed
whenever an instance
does not understand a message.
This mechanism is used
in certain somewhat complicated cases
like proxies and automatic delegation:
when you want a certain object
to transmit all the messages it gets
to another object.
The "does not understand" mechanism
can be used for that.
Default implementation
of "does not understand" is found
in the Object class.
It raises one exception.
The exception
is called "Message Not Understood."
So if the "DNU" method
of the Object class
is executed, an exception is raised.
That means the code you are writing
can catch the exception,
the way it would catch any exception.
The exception opens a debugger
for messages that are not understood.
In this example,
we return to the class "Node."
We have a "say hello" method in Node,
which sends a "coucou" message
to the receiver or self.
There's also a "welcome" method
that sends a "say hello" message
to self.
It provides special handling
in the context
of a misunderstood message.
If a message is not understood,
it will be handled.
Here, "say hello"
sends a "coucou" message to self.
"Coucou" is still unimplemented.
Ultimately,
the "does not understand" method
will be executed.
The "message not understood"
exception will be raised.
The code here, following on/do,
is used to catch exceptions,
like "try/catch" in Java.
A later sequence of the course
will go into these exceptions.
The point here is to notice
that this code
is the same as Java's "catch," and
it will be executed for every exception.
Say we send the message "welcome"
to Node 1.
Knowing that "coucou"
is not implemented,
the console will display "something
went wrong with the message."
What you should know:
When the lookup algorithm does not find
a method to match a message,
a "does not understand" message is sent
to the initial receiver,
with the first message as a parameter.
Each class can implement this method.
The default implementation in the Object
class will be executed.
This default implementation
raises an exception,
called "message not understood."
The code you are writing can catch
the exception
and subject it to debugging.