Hello! In this sequence,
we'll learn more about Seaside,
especially the part
that generates HTML.
You recall that all Seaside components
respond
to "renderContentOn" messages.
This message is what enables us
to generate the appropriate HTML code.
This method has a parameter
named HTML.
It is an object instance
of the WAHtmlCanvas class or subclass.
It is dedicated, offering the programmer
an API to generate valid HTML.
Our counter code is here.
The html object here is used to generate
headings, anchors, spaces, etc.
Today's sequence
goes further into this language.
The dedicated language
is made up of "brushes."
Each brush is dedicated to generating
a particular HTML tag.
The API is object-oriented.
Its very construction,
using message-sending to objects,
guarantees the validity
of the HTML code,
unless we have made
a messaging error.
Here's an example,
using the dedicated language.
I send the html object
the message "div"
which will render one object.
This object is a brush
dedicated to generating
html div codes.
It includes the "id" message,
and the message "with."
This generates a div with the attribute
id = title.
The character string identified
as Title will be part of the div.
I can generate
more complex things.
The beginning is the same:
html div id list.
This is my div line.
But I can put lots of other tags
inside the div.
Instead of sending a character string
to "with," I send a script.
Within that script,
I can reuse my html object
and other brushes
to generate other tags.
With "html span class item"
I generate a span
with a class attribute and content.
Now I can use loops.
This DSL is as powerful as Pharo.
Here, I generate an unorderedList.
It's abbreviated "ul."
It has an id list attribute.
I have list items
inside the unordered list.
They are here.
Only I generated them
using a loop.
I have a "to do 1 to 5" loop.
A classic Pharo loop.
I generate 5 list items
with an attribute
class... item...
followed by the name
of each list item.
I have concatenated the loop cursor.
Item 1, Item 2, Item 3, etc.
We can go one notch farther,
and code
for a different class selector CSS
for each list item,
depending on an odd or even loop cursor.
Typically, here, for example,
I use the message .class: if:
That means "add this class
if the following condition is true."
Here's the one for "even."
You can see that in the generated code,
the first list item
has this particular class CSS.
"itemodd."
The second item has this CSS class:
even.
This one is even, this one is odd,
etc., etc.
The syntax is concise.
It packs all the power of Pharo
to generate HTML using a DSL.
Another feature
of this dedicated language
is extensibility.
It is easy to make it support
modern CSS frameworks
like Bootstrap, for example.
This CSS framework
uses CSS classes
to generate attractive HTML elements,
like green or blue backgrounds, etc.
How do we go about
extending the dedicated language?
We have special brushes
like the one here.
They all have a "tbs" prefix,
meaning "twitter bootstrap."
I send the message "tbsAlert"
to my HTML object.
That means "generate an HTML div
or element
"compliant with
the Twitter Bootstrap framework."
Many brushes will refer
to the TBS framework.
I can render Twitter buttons
with "tbsButton."
And TBS button groups, this way.
You can see that these three buttons
all belong to one group.
To return to the example
of the counter, from last session:
We defined a simple counter.
Now I'll make
a Twitter Bootstrap version of it.
It's very easy. I make a subclass
of my earlier counter,
called "WATwitterCounter."
I go to the "class" side
of this class
and define the method
"initialize," which specifies:
"this component will be using
the TBS development library."
Here is TBSDevelopmentLibrary
and JQDevelopmentLibrary.
Those are Javascript
and CSS frameworks.
Next, I'll return to the instance side
of this class.
I'll define a new
renderContentOn method,
redefining the preceding one.
All my brushes will begin with tbs.
"tbsButtonGroup," "tbsButton,"
etc., etc.
But this doesn't change
my regular code,
still consisting of callbacks
with "self increase"
and "self decrease."
It doesn't change a thing.
The only parts that use TBS
are the HTML rendering brushes.
Now we'll see
what my new counter looks like.
The plus and minus buttons
are together in my Button Group.
And counter value is displayed
on a badge,
in this Bootstrap version.
You can go even farther,
beyond Bootstrap.
You can define your own style rules.
For example, here, I decided to say
that I want all "odd" elements
to be in the "odd" class.
Every time I render the counter value
here, as a TBS badge...
That is, the counter value
will be displayed...
But I'm adding the CSS class "odd"
only if the value is odd.
The CSS class is added
only if this condition is true.
I defined the CSS class "odd"
by defining the method "style"
on my counter.
It will render a character string
according to CSS style rules.
".odd color: red"
will make the counter red
for odd numbers.
To sum up:
A web application is a root component.
Seaside is a root component.
All components can be rendered
in HTML using renderContentOn.
And we have a dedicated language
that is powerful and extensible.
It enables us to generate HTML
easily, using brushes,
and an extensibility that supports
existing CSS frameworks
like Bootstrap, JQuery, UI, etc.
You can take advantage
of Pharo's scripting powers like loops,
to generate arrays of elements
easily.