Hello, and welcome back
to the Pharo course.
This segment
covers two more aspects.
I'll cover them in depth.
You'll use them yourselves
in the TinyBlog exercises.
First, what web development can we do
once we have described data?
Second, how does Seaside use REST?
Seaside is one of the frameworks
for REST in Pharo.
Let's start with the first subject.
Magritte is a framework
based on the hypothesis
that if you describe your data once,
it can generate several objects
based on this data.
Webforms and graphic interfaces,
for example.
In this course, I'll be focusing on
showing you how to generate
Seaside components
so that you can code
web applications faster.
We'll take the class "Address"
as an example.
These are Swiss addresses.
An address is defined
as a street, a place,
a postal code, and a canton.
I have an instance which describes
a particular street.
So far, this is just
standard programming.
Now, what Magritte does
is describe the fields
in the class.
It will describe a string in such a way
as to define it as a street name.
The postal code description
is more interesting.
First of all, we are going to say
an address is not valid
without a postal code.
Addresses lacking postal codes
are invalid.
And all Swiss postal codes
are figures between 1000 and 9999.
This is specified
in the NumberDescription.
This information can be taken
into account
for automatic form validation.
For Place, we also describe
it as required, and as place.
Moreover, in Switzerland,
there are 26 cantons.
The canton is part of a list,
so we have SingleOptionDescription.
It is required. We want it to be sorted,
and the options listed.
So the list of options
is limited to these 26.
Once that's done,
what can we do with Magritte?
Here is how the address
is described in Pharo.
We'll define a descriptionStreet
as a StringDescription,
with such and such a label
and priority.
For street numbers,
I define a NumberDescription:
I assign a different priority
and label.
I specify "Required"
and give my minimum and maximum values.
The very first thing
I can do with this description
is write a little tiny program
to interpret the address
and generate reports.
I take an address,
and run it through this program,
which generates a little report:
The name of the street,
The place - Bern,
and the canton, Bern.
Postal code 3012.
I can use the fact
that my data has been described
to generate reports.
That was the simplest kind.
But now we'll do more complex
things with Seaside,
like creating a visual component.
Here, I am saying,
"Address object, I want to see you
as a component."
That generates this part.
I'll add a validation form,
which gives me "Save" and "Cancel."
And I'll write a "call" command
so it displays.
As you can see, I managed all that
without even using the Seaside DSL.
Described, my web components
are generated automatically.
That's powerful!
Here is what the company Quuve does
Quuve is an American
portfolio management platform.
The whole display
was done with Seaside and Magritte.
All the reports
are generated automatically.
That's a serious gain
in productivity!
The idea of this course
is to give you some intuition
of what can be done
when you describe your data,
especially
with web component generation.
You'll do that in TinyBlog.
Now, I'll show you the potential
in Seaside's REST layer.
It enables client-server communication
in the absence of visual components.
REST is integrated into Seaside
smoothly.
Domain objects will be annotated.
You'll have a natural conversion
between URL parameters
and SmallTalk or Pharo methods.
To give you an idea of the complexity,
we'll define what we call a "filter":
TinyBlog Restful Filter.
is a subclass of WARestful -
it doesn't matter.
The important part is the filter I add
down here when I create my application.
You'll see it in the exercise.
Now, let's imagine
that I want to get all the blogs
that I have on my TinyBlog server.
Here's how:
First, I define a method
in the RestfulFilter class,
a method called listAll.
It corresponds to the anchor
I'm going to use:
I tell it to use its "get"
from the REST protocol
to generate text in json form.
I create a Pharo string stream
I want the stream to contain
all available blogs.
I'll take each blog -
and you see another iterator -
Take each blog
and convert it to Javascript,
separated by commas.
That gives me what I want.
Now we want to do something
a little more advanced.
Say I want to find a blog
by searching for a title match.
Here, I can use "post," for example.
I'll say I want this blog post,
by giving the title next to it.
I do that by defining a "post" method
that takes a title as a parameter
along with the "path" concept.
I tell it, when the URL
contains http..., post/
and something here,
those characters are the title.
That's what we see here,
inside the wavy brackets.
Likewise, I tell it,
that will produce text in json form.
Then what I do is call upon
TinyBlog functionalities.
I ask, do you have a post
with a title specified as a parameter?
Yes? If it's empty, I return an error.
Otherwise, I put it in my stream
and render my stream.
There are lots of things
we can do.
If I want to do a search,
it's the same thing.
In my URL line, I type
"search: title" with a value,
it will be matched automatically.
My title will appear here.
That's how you work with REST
in Seaside.
You can have your graphic components
in Seaside
and a way to expose
your domain functionalities
with a REST API.
I've only shown you "gets."
But all the other REST functionalities
are available:
Delete, Post, Get, etc.
I also showed you how Seaside,
paired with Magritte,
generates powerful forms,
automatically.
And REST is well integrated.
Often, people use Teapot
as a REST solution, as well.
It's a Zinc overlayer
for doing REST prototypes.
It's a quick way to find out
if their REST API is working.
Have fun with it.
There's documentation
in the Web Enterprise Book.