Hello.
This sequence covers
the Seaside web framework,
an innovative way
of building web apps in Pharo.
Seaside is powerful and flexible.
It is based on the concept
of reusable, stateful components,
on top of a stateless protocol,
HTTP, in Web applications.
Seaside is secure by default,
of course.
It integrates
all the latest Web 2.0 techniques,
like Ajax, etc.,
and REST architectures.
This is the Seaside URL.
You can refer to it for documentation
like the free online Seaside book.
It also offers a set
of Seaside tutorials.
Lastly, you can ask questions
on the Seaside mailing list.
An active community will reply
to any questions you may have.
A little history: Seaside
has been in production since 2002.
It is actively maintained.
The Seaside framework is the basis
for many Pharo success stories.
Those stories are online
on the Pharo site, pharo.org.
As you'll see,
there are many web projects,
and most use the Seaside framework.
As I was saying,
Seaside is a web framework
centered on the component concept.
These components
are reusable and stateful.
It has a domain-specific language
to render the components in HTML.
The rules for composing
these components
will be covered in a later sequence.
A web application
is just a root component.
Seaside makes it possible
to debug applications on the fly,
in the Pharo debugger.
In a later sequence of this course,
you will learn
how to use metadata
to generate forms automatically.
These are some of the examples
of web applications built with Seaside,
in production since 2002.
I'll zoom in on a few of them.
This application makes extensive use
of graphs,
and other interlocking components
that make a complex application.
Here's another example of an application
you can find on Pharo's website.
It features reporting tables
that are quite complex,
interlocking with each other.
That can be built very simply
with the Seaside framework.
The main concept in Seaside
is the component.
A component is a subclass
of WAComponent
supplied by the Seaside framework.
A component is reusable
and stateful.
It can be rendered in HTML
in the form of , etc.
In Seaside, a web application
has a root component -
in this case, WACounter,
saved in the system
as a web application.
It will be named "Counter," and
accessible as such, from the URL.
Here's an example of
my Counter application, in the URL.
It's a component
rendered in HTML, here.
The value of the counter is zero.
We have two links, here.
You click on ++
to increase the counter value,
and on --
to decrease the value.
The code for implementing
this application is very simple.
I create a subclass
of WAComponent: WACounter.
It has an instance variable
named count.
The initialization method
sets the counter to 0.
One method increases the value,
the other decreases it.
Now we need the HTML part,
so the counter is rendered in HTML.
All we have to do
is endow it with a method,
renderContentOn,
a parameter.
The parameter will help us
generate the HTML code.
Here's the example, with the addition
of "renderContentOn"
to the counter class.
I use this parameter,
a conventional Pharo object.
It's an instance of the class
WAHtmlCanvas, supplied by Seaside.
I send messages to this object
to generate the HTML code,
and a heading
and an anchor, or link.
The "callback" message
enables me to specify
a block of code to execute
when I click on the link.
Here, when I click on the link
called ++,
the "self increase" method
is executed.
Clicking on -- prompts the execution
of the "self decrease" method.
It's so simple.
If an error occurs when I click
on a link; i.e., in a callback,
I knowingly have inserted
a "halt" point. It could be an error.
I've inserted a halt point
in the decrease method.
"Self" will halt if the counter
is decreased below zero.
That will bring up the debugger.
As you see,
if I do this in my web application,
the debugger is displayed here.
Here's the program's application stack,
with the method "RenderContentOn"
and the decrease, here.
We did stop on haltIf.
I can modify the code right here,
press "Proceed,"
and my application
will receive the HTML response
as if nothing had happened.
Another problem in Web applications
is the "back" button.
When the user clicks on "back,"
it desynchronizes
the server and client.
Imagine I increase the counter 5 times.
Now it reads "5" on my screen.
Then I click on the back button
in my browser.
The counter now reads 4.
But the server isn't updated
about my back-button click.
So if I click again on ++,
the screen will display a 6.
The problem is, the server side
thought we were still on 5.
5+1 = 6.
Seaside makes it very easy
to handle the back button.
We define a new method
on the counter class: "states."
It will return the array
for which the state is to be preserved
when the back button is hit.
In this case, it is only
the object self: the counter.
Now, if I press "back,"
and then click on ++,
I should see 5 again.
Callbacks are actually
blocks of code
that contain all of Pharo's power.
I can write any Pharo code
in this callback.
I took a more complex example
here.
I can use an alternative "if"
to say if I increase the counter + 1
or + 2, depending on whether
the count is odd or even.
For even numbers, the counter
will increase faster than for odd.
As you see, Pharo
is really a powerful language
in these callback blocks.
To return to the preceding example,
if I click on ++ here,
it brings me to a new window,
telling me it is an even number.
Next, I'll show you
how to write a greeter application.
The user enters his first name.
He types it in here,
and when he clicks on "Say Hello,"
we want to display a string
of characters: "Hi" and the user name
he entered in the beginning, here.
It's very easy to code for that
in Seaside.
I create a subclass Component
of the class Greeter.
The instance variable
is Username.
The method renderContentOn
I'm showing you here
displays the field "Username."
The next line is textinput.
That's the text field you saw before,
where the user writes "Bob."
I will have one callback.
This time, it is a block
with a parameter, "value."
The value parameter of this block
will be the string of characters
the user entered.
We can store it
in the instance variable
of the Greeter component
UserName.
Next, when the "submit" button
is clicked,
I'm going to call a new component,
using the command selfinform.
I tell it to display the string
"Hi, Bob."
I concatenate the character string "Hi"
with the text entered as UserName.
I hope those of you who are used
to coding web applications
noticed that Seaside
does not require
manual request parsing to find
parameters in requests or URLs.
It does not require XML configuration
files, or indeed, files or pages.
I did not say anything
about links to the next page.
The only thing I talked about
was components:
objects and messages.
I talked about callbacks
and the ability to debug live,
using the Pharo debugger.
In sum, it's easy to build
web applications in Seaside.
There is one root component.
Components can be combined
to build more complex applications.
A component renders itself
in HTML with renderContentOn.
We have an extensible
domain-specific language
that generates HTML code
for each component.
We'll cover that in greater detail
in the next video.