Hello, this is a very advanced course.
We'll focus on
how Pharo organizes classes
and instance relationships
between classes.
It's really aimed at enthusiasts.
It's not essential to master,
since you already use Pharo without it.
You can use Pharo for programming
without knowing how it works.
But you may be unsatisfied if the course
didn't explain how it functions.
Like explaining where "new" is defined,
or what the class of a metaclass is.
This video will explain all this stuff.
It doesn't matter
if you don't understand straightaway.
But if it really interests you,
you can watch it several times.
There is one fundamental key here.
It's a fun aspect,
which this transparency should explain.
The basic idea,
which we keep reiterating in this MOOC,
is that, as you should know,
when we send a message to an object,
we search in the object's class
via the instantiation link.
If it isn't there,
we follow the inheritance chain.
We always start in the class,
then follow the inheritance chain.
This rule must be followed
systematically.
To explain metaclasses,
we summarize them in seven points,
which are relatively simple.
Every object is an instance of a class.
That's difficult!
Look at this example.
The object OrderedCollection
is an instance of this class.
So far, it's clear.
The second point is that every class
inherits from the Object class.
As we see here,
OrderedCollection and upwards
inherit ultimately from Object.
Just a note for French speakers,
"eventually" means "ultimately."
It's confusing.
So,
we have our inheritance graph
that inevitably leads to Object.
What is the responsibility of Object?
It represents object behavior
common to all objects,
such as error handling,
inserting a halt, and announcements.
Object is the root
of the inheritance tree.
Its key responsibility
is minimum behavior.
Returning to our list, every class
is an instance of a metaclass.
We explained this in an earlier course.
A class X is the sole instance
of the metaclass named X class.
We see that the OrderedCollection class
is an instance of the class
OrderedCollection class.
It works the same way
for the SequenceableCollection class,
and the Object class
with the class Object class.
All classes are instances
of another metaclass,
which takes the same name
followed by "class."
Metaclasses are created
automatically when we create a class.
We send a "new" message
to the metaclass to create the class.
Next point.
Metaclass hierarchy
parallels class hierarchy.
Earlier, we explained that
OrderedCollection
is an instance of its class,
and likewise for SequenceableCollection.
Now we need to specify
the relationship between the two.
Since there's an inheritance
relationship here, there's also one here.
In all cases.
That's why we say
they are two parallel hierarchies.
When do we use this hierarchy?
If I send the "new" message
to OrderedCollection,
where do I search?
In the class.
I query in each class
whether or not "new" has been defined.
Moving upwards, has it defined "new"?
Yes or no.
Here we utilize the key
I mentioned at the beginning.
To send a message, start with the class
then follow the inheritance chain.
Up to this point,
it may seem clear,
but now other questions come up.
What is Object class an instance of?
You might wonder.
And what is the superclass
of Object class?
Does it work
if we send a message to a metaclass?
Or if we send a message
to whatever it is here?
Let's have a look.
The system says that every metaclass
inherits from Class,
right up to Behavior.
Let's look at that,
and answer the first question.
Object class is a class,
hence it inherits from Class.
Class inherits
from ClassDescription and Behavior.
Unlike in Pharo,
in other systems such as Lisp
these two elements are a single class.
Pharo divides them for reuse.
Metaclass can be attached
to ClassDescription
to utilize ClassDescription
in two cases.
We see that Behavior,
which represents the essence of a class,
inherits from Object.
So, if I send a message here,
it will travel all the way up to here.
It follows the inheritance tree
from the Class level.
Now we want to know
where "new" is defined.
The method for creating instances
is defined in Behavior.
When I send the "new" message
to OrderedCollection, what happens?
First, I search in the class.
Suppose that "new" is not redefined
in the inheritance,
so I search all of the superclasses
until we find "new."
In a lookup, we search for a method
and execute it on the receiver.
So, I find the "new" method
and execute it on the receiver,
the class OrderedCollection,
which creates a new instance
that we'll name 3 4, for example.
Okay?
We're using the key I spoke about.
We search the inheritance chain,
starting with the receiver's class.
In a nutshell,
what does Behavior represent?
It's the essence of an object
that can have instances.
Objects with instances
must include a superclass link,
method dictionary,
and description of instances (format).
The methods shown here include
examples such as new, basicNew and new:.
The difference between new and basicNew
is that you must never
redefine basicNew.
As we explained
in the course on methods,
if you redefine a method starting
with "basic," the method is inaccessible.
The original method.
There are other ways to access
the compiled methods, as shown here.
Behavior is the essence of a class.
What is ClassDescription?
It's an abstract superclass
shared by Class and Metaclass.
It adds facilities to Behavior,
such as naming instance variables,
since class execution can be automatic.
ClassDescription adds such things.
Category organization concerns methods
in your browser showing the protocols.
For example, a method can be stored
in the printing protocol.
Also, the notion of a name.
Plus the maintenance of Change sets
and the saving of changes in files.
You can look at that yourself.
This categorization exists because
use is shared by Class and Metaclass.
The responsibility of Class
is to represent the classes
we employ in Pharo.
This includes representation
for classVariable names
and a better way of naming
and compiling elements.
Once again, refer to the code.
Classes are instances of metaclasses.
If Object is an instance
of a class named Object class,
and likewise for OrderedCollection,
the same applies to Class,
ClassDescription, and Behavior.
So, Class is an instance of Class class
and ClassDescription is an instance
of ClassDescription class.
The same applies to Behavior.
We must also look at
the inheritance chain.
If there's an inheritance relationship
between these two elements,
the same relationship exists
here on the right.
As you see here,
we can trace the inheritance chain.
Behavior class therefore inherits
from Object class.
Now for the second last point.
Since every class is an instance
of a metaclass, a question arises.
What is OrderedCollection class
an instance of?
Since everything is an object in Pharo.
OrderedCollection class
is therefore an instance of Metaclass.
Object class and Class class
are instances of Metaclass.
All the metaclasses in the system
Furthermore, Metaclass inherits
from ClassDescription.
It's an unusual class
because it only has one instance.
And you can't name it because its name
is defined by its instance.
That may seem barbaric.
So, we see that OrderedCollection
is an instance of OrderedCollection
class, which takes its name.
All metaclasses
are instances of Metaclass.
In the code,
the main responsibility of Metaclass
is to create and initialize
a single instance of itself.
There's only one question
left to answer.
What is Metaclass an instance of?
Because Metaclass is a class,
like OrderedCollection,
it is an instance
of the class Metaclass class.
You'll see that Metaclass
inherits from ClassDescription,
therefore Metaclass class
inherits from ClassDescription class.
OrderedCollection class
inherits from Object class
as OrderedCollection
inherits from Object.
So, Metaclass is an instance
of Metaclass class.
OrderedCollection is an instance
of OrderedCollection class.
And Metaclass class
is an instance of Metaclass,
just as Class class and Object class
are instances of Metaclass.
This loop may seem bizarre,
but it makes sense in context.
You don't need this to use Pharo,
so feel free to overlook it.
But as this graph shows,
the key we spoke about earlier
works perfectly.
Every time we send a message
to an object, we look at its class
and its inheritance tree,
as shown in these examples.
If I send a message to this instance,
it leads me to Object.
If I send a message to the class,
I go to the metaclass
and follow the inheritance.
If I send a message to a metaclass,
where should I look?
In Metaclass, since the metaclass
is an instance of Metaclass.
I follow the instantiation link
to the end.
This is when a message is not understood
or a method is only defined in Object.
Now, what if I send a message
to Metaclass itself?
Where do I search?
First in Metaclass class,
then I follow the inheritance chain.
So... oops!
It gets more complicated here.
Similarly, if I send a message
to Metaclass class,
or to OrderedCollection class,
I look in the instance
of Metaclass class, which is Metaclass.
Like for OrderedCollection class,
I follow this path.
You will see
that this graph is entirely logical.
We cannot have an inconsistent graph
since the virtual machine
only does one thing.
It looks for messages in the class
and follows the inheritance chain.
This comprehensive graph
is consistent with that process.
I find this exciting because
I wondered about it myself.
So, to sum up, classes are objects
and can receive messages.
The procedure is the same
for all objects,
even if there are metaclasses
with a sole instance,
which are not explicitly named.
But it's not essential to know that.