Hello, this is the final chapter
in our journey into the world of Pharo.
It will complete the courses
we have presented.
It's important to understand
that the hard part is over
now you know the key aspects of Pharo.
We've covered pretty much everything,
except some
software engineering concepts,
like package dependency
and continuous integration.
You'll find them on www.pharo.org.
You will have learned
almost all of the core libraries.
There are others,
but they are extensions,
which have the same level of complexity.
For these, you'll need to learn
the specific libraries.
I hope you see Pharo
as an immersive system.
It allows you
to constantly interact with objects.
Particularly by coding in the debugger.
The debugger is a key to productivity,
so make sure you use it!
There's also another important aspect.
If you use Pharo for business,
contact us if you need help.
Pharo is a community of people
who do business in a concrete way.
Pharo is a young language
that is evolving.
Infrastructure is constantly improving,
as in its compiler, tools, and libraries.
Our community
is also constantly growing.
This slide shows Pharo's mid-term vision
with a list of projects in development
that will be realized in a year or two.
Briefly, these include scripting syntax,
an improved module system,
integration with versioning systems,
and integration with OSes.
All these features will be completed
within two years.
Today, Pharo is no longer
a small team working in France.
We have 70 regular contributors
across the globe who improve Pharo.
This community works on
numerous projects.
We don't even know what they all are!
Our message
is that you can participate, too.
You can take on a project
with other people.
It's very rewarding on many levels.
You can contribute to the system
and it's fun!
I hope you enjoyed this journey
and learned a lot.
I hope Pharo helps you to reflect
on the future of programming.
Everything is accessible in Pharo.
It allows you to do things
you can't do elsewhere.
But Pharo is more than that!
It's fun and elegant.
It's simple and pure.
Pharo is fantastic for developers
who want to program practical things.
For teaching objects, it's tops!