Hello. This week,
we'll get to the heart of the matter,
about syntax especially.
This class will be mostly about dealing
with the messages of Pharo's syntax,
which is most of Pharo.
In Pharo, there are three main things:
objects, messages,
and closures called blocks.
There'll be a course about blocks.
You can cover almost
the entire syntax of Pharo with this.
Pharo's syntax stems
from that of Smalltalk
which was designed
to teach children how to program.
It's about writing programs
which are like short sentences
a child might write.
It's also about minimizing
the number of parentheses.
We'll see how it works.
For instance,
let's take a tile on openstreetmap.
I want to open it in a graphic window.
This is an example of the syntax.
I use parentheses
because I want to get a png file first.
I convert the png file
into a Pharo graphic object
before opening it in a window: do it
with Pharo and you'll get the result.
It'll probably be water
as there are many water tiles.
In Pharo's syntax,
there are three types of messages
to minimize the number of parentheses.
There are unary, binary,
and keyword messages.
Let's see about them.
With unary messages, you have
one receiver then the method's name.
With binary messages, one receiver,
the selector, then an argument.
With keyword messages, one receiver,
then one argument or arguments.
You can distinguish them
thanks to the colon here.
We'll study this.
What is the use
of these three types of messages?
You can differentiate them.
It changes the way
programs are executed.
You always execute
what's between parentheses first;
then unary messages;
then binary; then keywords.
When at the same level,
you use the same order,
from left to right.
Let's see about unary messages:
if I ask small integer 1 what
its class is, it'll return SmallInteger.
This will be your homework
for next week:
if I send the message not to the Boolean
false, I get the Boolean true.
If I query the class Date
for today's date,
it'll return 24 May 2009, for instance,
which is a Date Object.
If I send the message pi
to the class Float,
it'll return a representation
of the object pi.
I don't know whether you noticed,
but I sent messages to objects
as well as messages to classes
in the exact same way.
I didn't say: "It's a class.
Careful, you have to do something."
I send the message class to the small
integer, it returns the class.
I send the message today
to the class Date, it returns a date.
Nothing fancy.
In Pharo, classes are also objects.
Messages sent to classes are processed
like messages to instances.
Which makes complete sense.
I have an example for you.
This exercise isn't related to syntax.
It's just to have fun.
I thought it would be fun to determine
what are all the methods
implemented in the class Point.
It's a unary message. I can say:
"class Point, return all your methods
and the message names you understand."
It'll return a long list
with all the messages.
See how easily you can build tools?
If I put this in a list,
I'll get a list
with all the messages the class returns.
That's how the browser you'll use works.
Let's refine this:
I'd like to query the system
for all the unary selectors
of the class Point.
I write it like this:
"Class Point, list all your selectors."
It'll return an array, a collection.
I write that I want to select...
This is a keyword message.
I want to select among the selectors
those which are unary.
There's a query called #isUnary.
It's a message about method names
which selects such things.
This is a small footnote in the syntax.
You'll learn about it in the course
about iterators, select: being one.
It's very elegant:
I can query the system in one line.
Back to the subject at hand.
There are binary messages:
they are composed of anObject,
aBinarySelector, anArgument.
Binary selectors are a combination
of these incomprehensible things:
%, |...
What can't be understood is binary.
What looks like math is binary.
For instance, I send the message +
to the object 1
with the object 2 as argument.
It returns 3, which is great.
> is a binary message.
@ is also a binary message
(it creates points).
String concatenation with a comma
is a binary message.
I write: 'Black chocolate','is good'
I get the string 'Black chocolate
is good'. Which is true.
About keyword messages...
People often find them frustrating
when they're used
to a Java-like or C-like syntax,
with a period, parentheses,
and a comma in the middle.
But we do it like this: in the middle.
What you have to see in this example
is that the message is:
kayword1keyword2.
The message is full.
It's composed of two parts.
It's time to test yourself.
I'll give you a couple seconds.
What are these messages?
What types do they belong to?
The first has no argument:
it must be unary.
The second too.
There's a colon: it must be a keyword.
There's something with a comma
I don't understand: it's binary.
It's weird: it's binary.
There's no argument: it's unary.
There's a colon: it's a keyword.
It might seem difficult, but...
This is the solution.
For example,
let's imagine I want to change
the x value of a point.
This is a point. It's a binary message.
I write setX: with an argument.
It returns a point
in which 2 has been changed.
It doesn't look so hard, does it?
Now with the message at:put:.
I have an array.
It contains strings:
'Calvin' 'hates' 'Suzie'.
I want to change the second element.
I write at: 2 put: 'loves'.
This is 2. So 'loves' comes here.
About arrays, you can see
the method is called at:put:.
This method changes the value
of a collection at a given index.
As you can see, collections
start at 1 in Pharo, not at 0.
I want the second element,
so I count: 1, 2.
You don't have to subtract anything.
I'll give another example
of keyword messages:
when I ask whether 12,
which is an integer,
is between 10 and 20,
it's the message between: and:.
In the syntax, it would be the same as:
12.between
And(10,20).
I think I've focused on this enough.
There are three types of messages:
unary, binary, and keywords.
That's all.