-Hi. In this video, we are going to have
a look at the Inspector tool from Pharo
and how it can help you
inspect your objects from within
and have a real close look
at how they work
and how you can interact with them.
In order to use it,
I put up an expression that you certainly
will not see in real life.
Basically, it is an "OrderedDictionary"
with three key values.
Under the key "Time",
I put the "Time now",
under the "Date", the "Date today",
and under a "Morph" key,
I put an "HSVAColorSelectorMorph".
We will see what it looks like later on.
If I want to open the Inspector
on this particular object,
I can right-click and go to "Inspect it"
or simply press the shortcut Cmd+I.
So, let's click on it.
We can see
that the Inspector is now open.
I will just tidy the Playground.
Now the Items tab is really interesting
but we will go over the Row tab first.
The Row tab shows you the actual
limitation of the "OrderedDictionary".
For example,
we have got the self representation
being the OrderedDictionary
with the three pairs of key values,
"Time", "time now", "Date", "date today",
and a certain Morph
that we will see later.
We have got the dictionary
and the ordered keys.
If I click on the dictionary,
we will see that there is another tab
that will open on the right.
The nice thing that we can see there
is that we can, for example,
click another time
on the Array this time.
And we can see
that we now have three windows
and we can have a preview
of the first one below the window.
I can extend it.
I have got the three views
or I can restrict it to the last one.
Right now, I am in the last one
and a nice thing is that I can interact
with this Array object
by for example writing "self at: 1"
and I can print this
and it will say that 1 has "Morph"
associated
with the "HSVAColorSelectorMorph".
If I want to go back to the other,
I can simply drag this back,
put it there or I can close it here
to have our two previous views.
Now, let's close this one,
we will have a closer look
to the Items tab
which is not represented in everything.
For example, if I go there
and I go to the 1 time,
you can see
that we have a different representation.
A nice thing that we can look at is...
Under String,
the items will be the number of
the different characters with the index.
Here, for the Array, we will have
the index and the different items
and if I go to the items
for the OrderedDictionary
and close those too,
you can see that we have
three different pairs of key values,
for "Time", we have the "time now",
"Date" with "date now",
"Morph" with a certain Morph.
If I click on the "Time" thing,
you can see that we now have
a panel open with the time.
We can go over to Details,
I can show you
the different keys and things
that are present for the "Time" object.
We can also go there
and write "self browse"
and press Cmd+D to do it.
This will open the System Browser
on the actual Kernel package
and the Chronology tab.
And we can have a deeper look
inside the actual Time class.
Another thing you can do
right from within the Inspector
is to go over to the Meta tab.
There, you can access
the different methods of "Time"
and its class hierarchy.
So, we can go inside Magnitude,
Object or even ProtoObject.
You can filter everything.
For example,
if I want to look at duration,
I can see
that it will filter everything else out.
We can filter the different classes
if you have a complex hierarchy
and now, if we go to "Date",
you can see that this time,
I have got another tab called Calendar.
We do not have the tab items anymore
but we have got a calendar tab
that is a special tab made
for this subject
that will show us
that we are May 10th, 2020
and that it is located here
on the calendar.
Now, a nice thing we can see
is that if we go over
to the "Morph" object,
it is a really complex object
because we have several bounds.
We do not really know
how any of this works,
but we can open it in world.
"OpeninWorld".
Let's do that.
We can have a small look at it.
We have got a color selector,
then we have got
some kind of selector as well here
and a transparency selector there.
We can see that we can inspect
this object from here
by using "SelectedColor".
Now, if we would like to plug this color
in the Inspector,
we can right-click
and instead of doing
"Do it" or "Print it",
we can press "Do it and go" or Cmd+G.
This will plug the results
in the Inspector if I click there.
We can now see that we have got
this color right there.
That is really powerful.
Another thing you can do
is open the object twice.
If I go there, I will click on "self".
I will remove the first tab.
What we can do,
instead of exploring this complex object,
is go to Submorphs.
And on this, I go to Morph.
This is the "HSVAColorSelectorMorph"
all together.
Now, we can explore the tree composition
and if I click on, for example,
the "HColorSelectorMorph",
it will show me exactly what it is
and I can inspect it,
inspect the raw code
of this particular piece of Morph.
I can do the same thing there
and you can see that it will add
the different components
or show me exactly
what I am looking for.
The Inspector is a really nice way
to have a close look at your objects
and interact with them
from within them.
You can even interact
with the actual hierarchy,
browse for classes.
A nice thing you can do is implement
new tabs for your objects,
such as for example the Submorphs tab
or the Morph tab,
we had the Calendar tab for the date,
or the items for the different iterables.
So, the Inspector is a really nice way
to understand how the objects work.