"Working with scoped operations"
Quentin Ducasse.
-Hi. In this video,
we are going to look at the packages
and how you can handle them
in the System Browser.
If you remember correctly,
the System Browser can be accessed
via your environment,
go into Tools, then System Browser.
All the packages are there on the left
and you can see that some of them
have triangles on their left side.
This basically will show you
all the different tags
that have been used on this package.
What does that mean?
Basically, if you click on the package,
you will see all the classes
from within it
and if you click on one of the tags,
for example Parser,
you can see that those classes
have been defined
using AST-Core-Parser.
This means that you can really
structure your package as you want
and this will help you navigate inside it
and this will give out the structure
more clearly
for your readers, proofreaders
or any other developer working on it.
Once again, you can simply do it
by using the name of the package,
"dash" the name of your tag.
Another important thing
that you can filter out
from the different packages
is by using collections.
For example,
this will show you all the packages
having collections in their name.
And another thing you can do
is set up a scope
so you have the scoped view here.
If I click for example on AST-Core,
click on Scoped View,
I will only have this one
that will show up.
And I can also right-click
and go to Set up scope.
This will help me create a scope
with only the packages I need,
for example the three AST ones.
OK.
This will make your System Browser
count only those three packages.
So, what this will do
is only show you those three,
but it will also restrict the actions
you have on them, only on those three.
This will control the actions
you have on your environment
and restricts them
to only these three packages.
We saw how we can tag,
create tags inside packages
and set up a view
in the System Browser.