"Browsing a class"
Quentin Ducasse.
-Hi.
In this video, we are going
to look at the System Browser,
which is a tool that helps you write
and navigate inside code,
packages, classes.
In order to find it, you simply have
to go to your Pharo environment,
left-click and go to Tools,
then System Browser.
Just click on that.
This window will pop up
with four columns.
The column on the left consists
of all the packages
that are present in your Pharo image.
You can see
that there are quite a lot of them.
If you want to go
inside one of these packages,
you simply have to click on it.
For example, let's go inside AST-Core.
Click on it.
You can see
that this column is now filled
and you can see
that those are all the classes
that are inside this package.
Now, if we want to go inside a class,
simply click on it
and you will see that the next
two columns will fill in as well.
The column on the right
consists of all the methods
that are in the RBComment class.
This one consists of protocols.
Protocols are tags
or groups of methods.
For example, right here, when we click,
we will have all the methods of the class
but if you want to filter
those methods a bit,
for example display only the ones
that belong to the printing protocol,
you can click on "printing" and see
that only printOn is filtered out.
Now, if we want to look
inside the body of a method,
we can click on it and you will see
that its body will appear here.
You can really investigate the packages,
classes and methods with this tool.
Now, another thing to note
is that you can look
at the class definition here
and the comments of the class
right there.
This is a small introduction
to the System Browser tool.
We will look into it a bit more
in the next videos.