I’d like to show you tips
to be more efficient
when you select an expression
to execute it.
So, let’s imagine we have this
3-lines expression.
If I want to execute the first
line, what can I do?
I can place the cursor at the
beginning of the line
and select the end,
or the end and select toward the beginning.
So here it works.
Now, what I can do: I can
double-click
at the end of the line to select it.
And even better : I can place
the cursor
anywhere on the line and execute it.
I press “Escape” to unselect.
Now, if I want to select 2 lines,
I will select normally, as I’ve
shown you before.
So here I get 1000.
And now, if I want to select
the whole expression,
what can I do?
I can do the same thing than
previously or I
can place the cursor at the end
of the expression,
and double-click, or at the beginning
of the expression and double-click.