In this video, I will show
you how to
create a package, a class, and
describe tests.
The first thing to do is to
open the system browser.
The system browser enables to browse
packages.
Here there are packages.
The first thing to do is
to create a package.
We will click on “Add
package”, "MyCounter".
As there are many packages
and we don’t want
to see them, it is a good thing
to filter this.
We have our package "MyCounter".
And there, we define a class
that we call
"Counter" and it has an instance
variable “count”.
The little orange icon means
that the code has not been saved.
Here, we will compile code
with the “Accept” function.
And here, the class
"Counter" has been compiled.
The system searches a little
and says that there are
good comments. We will see this later.
For the moment, we don’t care.
There is a red exclamation mark
because we haven’t written
a comment.
So, we will write a first
comment:
"I'm a simple counter…”
We write a little example
so that the counter understands
how it will work:
Counter new,
Counter increment, increment,
Counter
count. Here it should be equal to 2.
Once more, the text hasn’t been
saved and we will compile it.
It has been saved.
We don’t have a counter anymore.
Now, we are going to define
accessors.
We generally put accessors in the
Accessing protocol.
We write: "count returns count".
In the same way, we write
aNumber, we do a Setter.
You see, I modified the count
method.
You can think that it has been
lost, but no, because
each time I change a method
using a different name,
it creates a new method.
I compile the new method,
I have “count”.
Now, we really want to test
and write our first little program.
I open Playground.
I create a counter,
we go on another line.
I put a value:
C count 7. If I ask for its
value, what will it
return? It will return 7.
Now, what we’d really like
to write
this as a test because like this
we can’t execute it
and we’d like to execute it
automatically.
We create a test class.
How do we create a test class
in Pharo?
We change the super class,
we say it inherits this
from TestCase and we will
define a test class
called CounterTest.
Now, I will compile it.
I have a new CounterTest class
in my system.
I will define a new method,
I will add
a protocol called tests.
There I can define a new method.
Tests methods must always start
by “test”
and be in a class that inherits
from TestCase.
We will call it
"testCounterisSetAndRead"
for instance. We almost have our
test. We have already
almost written everything.
We will indent it a little better.
I create my counter.
And now, I write
"self assert
equals 7". This sentence is
strictly equivalent to
"self assert C count equals 7".
It is more convenient,
when you make a mistake
the return is smarter
when you use the first sentence.
We will compile.
Now, I can make my test executed,
my test is green. When you have
a test and it is green,
it is the right time to
save your production, your code.
In Pharo, you can save the image.
Here, that’s what I do, I will
save the image, but the image
is not satisfactory..
I’d like to show you
how you can save code
in a versions system.
Here, as I don’t know if you will
have an Internet access,
I will do it in my local cache.
You see, I have this directory
pointing toward
all those packages
on which I can work
and that I have loaded or not.
There, the system shows us that
several packages with modifications
haven’t been saved.
We don’t care about the first 2,
but we see that
MyPackage has a star. It means
there is code in
the image that hasn’t been saved.
Here that’s what I’m going to
do: I click on Save,
I choose the repository.
I click on save.
I write "first version
with accessors and a
green test".
I accept. Now it has saved
one package.
We will check.
I can open this directory.
If I look, I contains
lots of packages that have been
loaded by the system.
But in particular, if I filter,
I find
my package with its versions.
I advice you to save,each time
you add
a feature, and that’s what
we will do.
Now we will define
a test before implementing it.
We will write a test for
what is the increment
of a
counter. "TestIncrement"
What do we want to obtain?
We want to say it “I create
a counter,
I assign it a default value,
then I increment twice this counter.
“What should I check?”
I should check that the counter
has the correct value.
I compile. My test
is red as I didn’t implement
counter.
The operations in counter
increment and decrement.
I add
"operations increment".
What will we do?
We do "self
count 2: self count +
1". If we use systematically
accessors
internally or not, it depends,
it is a question of style.
in the same way, as it is very close,
we will define "decrement".
You see that on increment, there is
a test so I can
execute it and my test is green.
So I do have 2 tests that work well.
If I go in the test class,
all my tests are green.
What am I going to do?
I save. I will make a new save.
I will write "Added
increment and decrement".
Now if I look,
I have 2 versions
of my packages.
We will write a test for "decrement"
because there’s no reason
not to do it.
"Decrement", for instance I
could attribute the value 2
if I want
and I decrement twice. I should get 0.
My test is green so
I will save.
Now, what we want is if I look
and I write "Counter new"
and then
"Print it", it displays a counter
which value I don’t know,
so it is not very useful.
We would like to modify
this behaviour.
To do this, we will add
a method
called ”PrintOn",
in the Printing protocol.
Print on is a method called
by the system each time
you do PrintStream.
It has aStream as an argument.
What do we do?
We say that we’d like
to have a counter.
Here typically, I use the above
functions.
Now what I will do,
I’d like
to add a little
text
for instance
"with value" and "self count".
I do this because it is a
number, so I have
to get a textual representation.
I write "cr".
I compile.
The system tells me that I could do
better, but no matter…
For now we don’t care.
I can write "Counter new".
I look, it says that it is a counter
with a nil value.
That’s normal because I
haven’t initialised it yet.
Now we will add a support
to the initialisation.
To do this, we begin to write a test.
I say: “At the creation,
I want the values
to be 0.
What will I do?
I will write “self asser”
I check that "Counter new
count = 0".
There, what do we notice?
My test is false. Why?
Because if I do this,
I get nil.
As it is a class and I don’t
get access to
instance variables of the
CounterTest class,
I can select the expression and
execute it directly.
Once I have this test that isn’t
valid,
what should I do?
I will add an initialize method
in the initialisation protocol.
And there what do I do?
I write "super
initialize", and I will
say "count 2 points = 0".
This method is used each time
I add the “new” method.
Now I can look at my tests,
it’s green.
In the same way, if I write
"count", I get 0.
Once more, we will save:
"added printOn"
"added initialize + tests".
Now what is interesting is that
I can see all my history.
I can also see and browse this history.
If I click on “version”, I can
see the difference between these 2 systems.
Changes between version 3 and version 4
are ”initialize" "printOn" and the Test.
If I want the difference
between
version 2 and version 4,
I have all these changes.
Now, I remains one thing to do,
I’d like
to change a little the
way objects are created.
I start off by creating
a test that will clarify
what I want to get.
I will define a test
called
"AlternateClassCreation".
What do we want to obtain?
Let's say, I want to
be sure that
that Counter withValue: 19
If I do increment on it
and I ask for its value,
it must return 20,
Ok.
Let's add a parenthesis here,
it's better.
So, once more, the
test isn't ok,
and the assistant tells me:
"you send an unknown message".
You must notice that the message
withValue
is no more sent to an object
but to a class.
It means I have to define this
message
on a class.
So I select the class.
Now I go to class level
and I add
a protocol called
instance creation
withValue: aNumber
So what do I have to do?
The first thing to do is
to create a counter, a counter
variable,
counter, I do it slowly,
self new
So I create a counter
and I write
self count: aNumber
and I return this counter.
We can do it in a shorter
way
but for the moment let's
do it simply.
I compile my method.
And now it means I can
send messages.
You see, when I click on
this button,
I go on the class level.
I go from the class level
je passe au niveau classe.
Donc je passe du niveau classe
to the instance level.
Here I was on the class level
and here I go back on
the messages sent to
instances.
What does it means?
It means that if I do
Counter withValue: 18,
what will I get?
I will get an instance of the
counter class.
I get a counter with
value 18.
And here I could do
decrement.
If I refresh, I do get 17.
Know if I look at my test,
all my tests are ok,
so I will once more
save and I'm done.
Added instance creation
API and tests.
Done for now.