In this video, I will
present a cool tool
which help you to learn
Pharo by yourself
It is ProfStef.
How to launch ProfStef?
You type "ProfStef Go", select it,
then "Do it", and you are in ProfStef.
So, ProfStef is a small
tool written in Pharo.
What is interesting is that
it only uses Pharo syntax.
All you will see,
all you will manipulate,
are Pharo expressions.
For example, here, you have
a Pharo comment
that explains to do "Hello"
then, "Select the text",
use right-click and
choose "do it".
We will do it using
keyboard shortcuts.
Et voilà, I moved to
the second lesson.
Now you understood the principle,
some comments, and now some
expressions to execute.
If I do "Do it',
it opens a workspace and
I can type text inside, I close it.
This expression opens
a window that displays
the system version I am using
to record this video.
And to go to next lesson:
I select the expression, or not,
I can just put the caret
on the line, "Do it", and
I go to the next lesson.
This new lesson,
tells you that you were able
to achieve "Do it"
Now, I will do "Print".
Same as before, you have results
and you will see and interact.
So here, for example,
What is the current date?
March, 5th.
Voilà, you have seen all you need
to achieve to ProfStef lessons
by yourself.
And you will see that it is fun ;-)
I would like to thank
Laurent Lafont who is
the author of ProfStef because
it is a really cool tool.
So, we will do
"ProfStef says: #Thanks to:
#Laurent". Thanks again.
Obviously, this
expression cannot be executed
directly, so let's go to
the next lesson.