In this session we'll see
the Pharo object model.
We'll take an overview to show you
its elegance and simplicity.
You don't need
to understand everything now
because we'll go over these notions
over the next few weeks.
In Pharo
there are only objects and messages.
There are lots of objects,
to represent the mouse pointer,
booleans, arrays,
numbers, strings,
windows, scrollbars and so on...
Even compilers,
system objects such as sockets,
fonts, collections and so on.
All these are objects
to which we can send messages.
There are lots of different messages.
You can send size to a collection
to get its size.
There are the messages
plus, at:put:, do: and so on.
Objects and messages.
The messages indicate
the programmer's intention.
When I send a message to an object,
I'm asking it to do something.
It's really a request
made to the object.
And the object decides
what method to use.
This is the how. How to achieve
the programmer's intention
by deciding what method to employ.
Next we have another concept,
which is that of closure.
These are lexical closures,
blocks,
sorts of anonymous methods in Pharo.
We call them blocks.
This is important vocabulary.
Blocks are delimited
by square brackets, as you see here.
So all this is a block.
So you should really look at this
as an anonymous method.
In Pharo we have
a very simple and uniform model.
Everything is an object,
an instance of a class.
Even classes and messages
are objects too.
And all computations between objects
are done via message passing.
We really talk
about sending a message,
that's the term,
and not about executing a method,
because when you send a message
to an object,
there's a particular algorithm
called the method lookup,
just one algorithm,
which selects the right method to use.
The methods are virtually bound.
They accept late binding.
I send a message to an object,
and the method lookup
selects the right method.
We'll come back to that
in a dedicated session.
The Pharo object model is as follows.
Instance variables are protected.
All objects have instance variables
and they're protected.
They're private to the object
or are accessible from subclasses.
The methods are public
and virtually bound.
All the methods are public in Pharo.
And Pharo accepts
single inheritance between classes.
A class can only have
one superclass.
Here's an example of code,
the cross-product of two points.
There's point1 and point2.
I multiply the x field of point1
by the y field of point2,
and subtract the multiplication
of the y field of point1
and the x field of point2.
It's an example of a computation
you can do in Pharo.
To create objects
we have special messages.
Here, for example,
if I send the message @
to the integer 10
with the argument 20,
it'll a create a Point,
an instance of the class Point.
The name of the message is @,
the integer
that received the message is 10,
the one before the name
of the message,
and the argument, after the name
of the message, is 20.
Here's another example.
I want to create a string
of characters like this one here.
How is this string obtained?
We've used a first chain here,
Pharo,
we've sent it the message comma,
as argument
we have the string is cool...
Which is here, right?
The meaning of the message comma
is the concatenation of strings.
The two strings are glued together
to produce a single string.
We can create objects directly
with the message new.
I send new to the class Monster
and I'll get an instance of the class:
aMonster.
I can create an instance
of the class Array,
by specifying new
and attributing a parameter,
which I do with a colon,
and then here the integer 6.
And I get an array of size 6.
We can have dedicated messages
to create objects,
and I can define
my own messages to a class.
I could create a class Tomagoshi,
with a method withHunger
and for this method
I'll give the integer 10.
This creates an instance
of the class Tomagoshi
by attributing a parameter.
So these are specialised messages
for object creation.
In this lecture we've seen an overview
of the Pharo object model.
You don't have to understand it all,
we'll come back to these notions.
But it's important to remember that
there are no constructors in Pharo,
no static methods,
type declarations, interfaces,
package/private/protected modifiers...
All those classic modifiers
you get in object languages.
There are no parametrized types,
no boxing/unboxing and so on.
And you'll see
that it's a really powerful language.
So, in Pharo,
everything is an object.
Computation is done
via messages sent to objects.
Methods are late bound.
There's an algorithm,
the method lookup,
which selects the right method
when an object receives a message.
There's the notion of blocks,
which are anonymous methods.
Very important in Pharo.
And we can send particular messages
to classes
to create objects.