In this session
we'll look at what Pharo is.
It's a pure object language.
But it's also an IDE,
an integrated development environment.
It's inspired by Smalltalk.
That's its spiritual father.
It's a powerful and elegant language
that's fun to program.
There's a great community of people
who do a variety of things with it.
What we'll try to teach you on
this course, with the help of videos,
is that it's a living system
you can script as you go.
You can take Pharo with its MIT
licence and do what you want with it.
When I say that Pharo is elegant
I have arguments to back that up.
The syntax fits on a postcard
and the simple
and powerful object model
takes up four lines.
I'll show you...
On this slide
you have the full Pharo syntax.
I mean "full", there's nothing else.
That doesn't mean you can understand
the syntax just by reading this slide.
We'll have several sessions,
deciphering
and helping you understand
how the syntax is structured.
But it gives you an idea
of the work to be done.
There's nothing else
but this syntax.
Likewise, the object model
is summed up on that slide.
Everything is dynamically typed,
everything is an object instance
of a class,
all methods are public virtual,
all attributes are protected,
and there's single inheritance.
There's no boxing,
no primitive and non-primitive type,
no generic type, and so on.
You have everything.
You just saw
the Pharo syntax and model.
We'll come back to that,
but it's just to give you an idea
of the system's complexity.
You have to realise that Pharo
is entirely written in itself.
What do I mean by Pharo?
I mean the strings, characters,
booleans, IDE, compiler, sockets...
Everything is written in Pharo.
So if you master this syntax,
written on one page, and this model,
then you'll have access
to the entirety of Pharo.
I think that this is exciting
intellectually
because you have
this tiny entrance door
into a gigantic world.
So if you look
at the title of this mooc,
it includes the word "immersive".
Why is this?
Because Pharo isn't a blackbox.
The entire system
is fully inspectable,
so you can go and see
how it's implemented.
And Pharo is reflective.
It has a representation of itself
that you can use
in order to understand it.
This means you can get completely
immersed in a world of objects.
I like this metaphor of the fish tank.
A language is usually a blackbox.
Pharo isn't a blackbox,
it's a fish tank,
where you can see the objects
and constituents of the system itself,
but you can also dive into the tank
and interact with the objects.
So it's really in that sense
that we're inviting you
to play with Pharo.
Here I'm showing you an example
of an immersive system.
What we call immersive
or interactive.
On the left you have the code.
On the right, what it produces.
Each time the programmer
presses the compilation key,
the screen goes blue
and the result is on the right.
He's constantly modifying his code
and seeing what he's doing
in the right-hand window.
You can do this
with any element of the system,
whether it's a socket, a file...
3D, like here.
But a web server would be the same.
The web server functions
and you can modify it as you go.
Now I'll show you
the supports available
if you want to work Pharo
outside this mooc.
There are several books,
all open source.
There's Pharo by Example,
for beginners, in several languages.
It's currently being updated
for Pharo 5.
Deep into Pharo is more advanced,
going into the libraries,
into less-known aspects
of the language and the tools.
There's
Enterprise Pharo, a Web Perspective,
which puts the emphasis
on web libraries,
like WebSockets,
HTTP/HTTPS servers
and templating.
They're all open source.
What we'll use mainly for this course
is a web framework, Seaside.
You have 300 pages available
at the indicated address.
You can read the book
if you want to know more.
But we'll give you all you need
to follow the mooc
without having to read the book too.
For those interested
in other aspects,
there's this book of about 300 pages
about the numerical methods in Pharo,
going from things
like statistical series,
to iterative algorithms and clustering.
I told you that Pharo
is a system to learn from.
I'll give you a few illustrations.
We'll see them again
in the videos.
Every graphic element of Pharo
that you click on...
With Cmd+Shift+Option,
you'll get a little menu
around the graphic element.
By using these menus,
you can go directly inside
and manipulate the visual elements
you're dealing with.
We'll show you what
an Inspector is,
an object that lets you manipulate
the properties of other objects,
and start to implement them.
We also have an object
called a Finder.
So I can ask the Finder
to find all the system's methods
that contain the word "match".
It shows me a list, and I can access
the method's code directly.
There's also a tool called Spotter,
which you get with Shift+Enter.
And you tell it what you want.
Spotter will help you find
classes, methods or resources.
You'll have videos
to explain all that.
But, again,
Spotter is written in Pharo itself.
The Finder has quite a nice function,
when you start learning Pharo.
There'll be a video about this too.
You can give examples and say:
"This is what I want to do but I don't
know how to write it in Pharo."
The Finder will look for methods.
I have an example.
I say: "I have two strings, AB and C.
I'd like to concatenate them."
And I know that the result
should be the string ABC.
It sounds simple.
So I say to the system:
"Give me the message,
if one exists,
"which will let me
concatenate these strings."
And that's what you can see here.
It says “,” is a method implemented
in SequencableCollection.
This will be sent to my first string,
and I'll get my third string.
You'll be able to use this Finder
on examples,
to make you quicker in Pharo.
In this Mooc we'll talk
about object oriented design, which is part
of the DNA of Pharo.
People who program in Pharo
think OO in an elegant way.
I'll show you the exercises
we'll be presenting.
We're often asked
how not is implemented.
People often wonder
if this is an interesting question.
It is interesting because
fundamental rules result from it.
It'll be part of the exercise.
Once you have Pharo
and you see how not is implemented,
you'll start thinking
in a different way.
This really is part of the culture
of people who use Pharo:
to think a design
in a really elegant way.
You can install Pharo
as described on the Pharo website.
Of course, during the MOOC
and on the FUN site,
you'll get all the instructions
for installing Pharo on any system.
Pharo is very easy to install,
as a drag and drop,
onto any OS.