In this video, I’d like
to show you an
hidden side of Spotter which is
very nice:
how we can use Spotter
to browse in the file system.
Here I call Spotter,
now I type
./ #files, for example, it will
display the files
at the root.
So I can see the files,
only if it can
say something…
So you see here that I
can access my files.
Now I can do something even
nicer, I can also visit
the #Directories.
Here for example, you see I have
the cache package with my infos.
Here it is a zipped format, which
is not
really recognised directly by
the system.
Now if I go into,
I can choose, I browse,
and there, when I have
a .png for example, Spotter
is smart enough
to discover that this is
a .png and display it as such.
Not displaying the bits
representing the
.png.
In the same way,
you have a script.
What is particularly nice is that
if you have
a Zip, you can go directly and
look inside it.
Here it is what I am doing,
I am
going into the Zip and once
more, it is
recursive, I can see my
.png as if I was browsing them.
So it is really nice.