In this session, I’d like
to show you
menus, and in particular the main
operations,
but what I’d like to do also
is to show you how to
learn keyboard shortcuts linked
to this menu.
In Pharo, if you go in “Settings”,
you will have the reminder shortcut,
we set it on “true”
and you will see what it does.
For instance, when I type
1 + 2 and I use the Print menus,
ah!
All of a sudden, the system
displays this little window
showing that I should use
cmd + P instead of the menu.
So that’s what we are going to do
from now.
So I do cmd + P and here it is:
I get my result.
So now, I’d like to show you
the difference between “Do it”,
“Print it”.
Then we will see “Inspect it”
and “Do it and go”.
So "Do it", basically it is cmd + D,
here I’ve done it,
you didn’t see it but
it means that I execute the expression,
I don’t care about the result.
"Print it" means I execute
the expression and I display the result.
So let’s imagine now that we
have “Workspace open”,
if I do
“Do it”, it opens, it executes
the message and it shows
me there, it opens the Workspace.
Now, if I do “Print it”, what do
I get?
I get a Workspace which is the graphical
representation of the result.
Now I can do something more
interesting,
I can do "Inspect it".
What will ”Inspect it"
do?
It will execute the expression,
so I get a
Workspace, and it will open
a special tool
enabling me to browse inside and to see,
to interact with this object.
Here it is a quite complex object
so I won’t go
and see inside,
it is just to show you.
In the same way, something very powerful
is cmd + I.
Now, the last one is
"Do it and go".
"Do it and go" means execute it
and open an inspector
but open it inside this window
so that there is not several windows.
And it will enable you to browse.
So here for example, if I click on
"bindings", I don’t know what
it is precisely.
Ok, it is a dictionary.
You see there is a little
navigation window which enables
to see the elements and to
go backward, to say
I don’t want to see this
or I can browse and go into
the system and see for instance
the keys,
there are none for “bindings”
for example.