Hello and welcome to this Mooc
on Pharo:
Live Object Programming in Pharo.
For this first lecture
I'll present the mooc's aims.
So what are they?
You'll learn to program in Pharo,
obviously.
It's important to understand
and master all the syntax,
the full syntax and model,
and the environment of Pharo.
It's not just a language,
it's a programming environment
with lots of tools.
We'll show you
some of the most useful ones.
The mooc won't limit itself
to just presenting Pharo.
We'll deeply understand
the object-oriented
fundamental mechanisms.
That's really interesting.
We'll illustrate these
with aspects of Pharo itself.
We will also, from time to time,
show you some design heuristics,
heuristics which will let you,
in your life as a programmer,
design applications
in a more elegant,
more extendable way.
You'll work on real examples
in this mooc,
and at the end
you'll deploy your own web app
that you'll have developed
from start to end.
The mooc is structured
over 7 weeks.
We'll start with syntactic aspects
of Pharo
so you can quickly start
doing exercises.
But we're also going to mix the points
linked to object design,
so that you'll quickly understand
certain aspects.
Then we'll look at aspects
linked to Pharo's core functions,
like file systems and so on.
The course isn't always linear.
In the final sessions
we'll go back over concepts,
to be sure you really understood
what we discussed
in the first sessions.
You'll have plenty of exercises
and mini projects.
As motivation, after two weeks
you'll have seen the full syntax
and the model,
and you'll be ready
to do some mini projects.
A quick word about us.
There are three of us,
three colleagues,
all experts
in object-oriented programming.
I've worked on traits
which influenced Perl,
Php and Scala.
We're experts
in object-oriented design.
We're part
of the Pharo core development group.
And we're authors of several
open-source books on the web.
I recommend them to you.
So why Pharo?
Setting aside that we developed it
and think it's a great language,
it's very interesting
from an educational point of view
because you'll be immersed
in a world of objects,
interacting with
and manipulating objects.
As an example,
loops don't exist
as constructers in Pharo.
They're messages sent to objects
that are collections.
Conditions are messages
sent to objects that are booleans.
So you'll constantly be interacting
with living objects
and your programs will be transformed
under your fingers.
The fact that Pharo
is fully written in itself
means you have a wide possibility
for discoveries.
Once you've understood
the syntactical aspects of Pharo,
the whole world
will open up to you,
because it's fully written in itself.
So, to sum up this voyage
that I'm inviting you on...
Pharo is pure and elegant.
There are very few concepts used.
It's fun to program because
of the interaction with objects.
It's highly productive.
Pharo is used in many universities
because of its teaching properties
and the positive aspects
that it teaches.
One point which is often overlooked
is that Pharo
is an empowering system.
Pharo isn't a blackbox.
You'll be able to see
how the system is implemented
and modify things.
The metaphor I often use
is that Pharo is a fish tank,
and you can jump into the tank
and swim with the fish!
That's very special.
We're going to show you some videos
which will explain those aspects.
You'll have access
to the entire system.