Hello.
In this lecture I want to show you
the vision behind Pharo.
Why are people taking part in Pharo?
This will help you to understand
where Pharo is going
and why people use it.
The basic idea is to create
a tool, an infrastructure,
which will enable people
to reinvent their future,
to use the web in new ways,
to create new tools,
new forms of computation and so on...
For this, the notion of an engine
is very important.
It means the infrastructure,
the compiler, the services
and that sort of thing.
On a twin track, there's the idea
of creating an ecosystem
in which innovation
creates new things
to give us a competitive edge,
and in which business can bloom.
So how do we understand
this metaphor of ecosystem?
Via the teachers. There are
30 universities around the world
which teach Pharo.
Via the research groups.
There are 15 or so research groups
doing software engineering,
but not only that,
around the world.
And via the companies.
The basic idea of Pharo
is not to be an academic language,
but to be a language used by people
in order to make money
and live off their programming.
You can see some success stories
on the website.
Here's the address.
You can really see
what people do with it.
I'm often surprised
at what people do with Pharo.
It's not just cool
because we say it is.
People do real stuff with it.
You have to realise
that for the development team
Pharo is a vehicle.
We're the guys in black
around the Formula 1 car.
We improve it every day.
Pharo isn't something finished,
it's something
that's constantly being improved.
It's quite young
for a programming language.
It began in 2008.
The more it advances,
the more exciting its future looks.
I'll say a bit about that.
Most companies
do web content now with Pharo
because the web stack is excellent.
We're going to use Seaside
in this course,
but we can also use REST.
There are several HTTP servers
that are used.
It's a company that developed
Pharo the HTTP server.
There's the micro server Teapot.
You have the WebSockets
and identifications.
Metadescription of data to avoid
generating automatic forms.
Connections to databases,
whether SQL or relational.
And loads of protocols.
Some come out every day.
People make packages
which cover these functions.
Pharo is open.
What this means is that you can help
and have an impact,
but at least read
and have access to Pharo.
One important thing
which people have trouble
putting into concrete terms
is that Pharo is a system
which enables you.
Here I'm showing you
a quotation from an American
who changed
a very fundamental aspect of Pharo:
the delay.
It's a function for adjusting
the concurrency in the system.
He found that it couldn't
be tested in isolation.
He suggested changes in Pharo
so these functions
could be tested individually.
And his changes
were incorporated into Pharo.
What's really interesting
- I'll let you read the quotation -
is that he says he was really amazed
that he could simply think of doing it
and do it.
And similarly, with this slide,
Turtles all the way down,
meaning there are objects
all the way down,
the creator of Seaside, who knew
ruby, python, scheme, objective-C,
developed Seaside
in Pharo's ancestor.
I asked him why he used Pharo.
He said, "Because I could."
"I can manipulate the stack
behind the programmers' backs
"and suggest an abstraction
I couldn't in another language."
This empowering
is really very interesting.
I want to talk
about the mid-term vision of Pharo.
What will Pharo be in about 5 years?
The core will be bootstrapped.
Meaning we'll be able
to reconstruct it from itself.
Which isn't possible
at the moment.
We'll have a better integration
with OSes and C.
We can imagine launching a Pharo app
in any C application.
It'll be a more modular system
with validated distributions.
If someone writes
an XML parser, for example,
you'll want to know
if it's passed all the tests,
if it functions
in whatever version of Pharo,
if the non-regression rules
are satisfied...
So really using software engineering
to validate
what is made around the world,
so the people using Pharo can be
assured of the level of quality.
There's an effort now to make tools
more powerful than they presently are.
The idea is to have a system
that can adapt
as well to a coffee machine
as to the cloud.
The Pharo development team
is working on this sort of thing.
It'll soon be available
for everyone.
So Pharo, with its aim
to have an impact on real life
and involve companies,
has created an industrial consortium.
The idea is to promote Pharo,
to sustain its constant development,
to improve its visibility
and provide support.
Here are some members
of the Pharo consortium.
There are small companies
but big ones too, like Lam Research and Thales.
And a lot of universities
and research groups.