-In this lecture,
I would like to show
that object-oriented design
models the world in a different fashion.
First, what you should know
is that there is not
one single model of the world.
It depends on your focus of attention.
For example, in a bank,
they model the risk in a different way
than in an insurance company,
because in an insurance company,
it is the key business aspect,
whereas in a bank, it is a side effect.
So, on the one hand, you do not have
a unique model of the world,
but in addition,
you have different means and ways
to model the world.
In the past,
we could use data-driven models,
that are more used in database systems,
object-oriented design,
procedural modeling and so on.
In this lecture,
we will compare procedural modeling
and object-oriented programming.
What is object orientation?
In fact, object orientation is a paradigm
in that it is not a technology.
Object-oriented design
is a way to represent the world
by simulating the world
as a set of collaborating
and decentralized entities.
The idea is to try
to minimize the complexity
or to handle the complexity
of what you are modeling,
and also increase the reusability
and lower the maintenance cost.
Let us compare procedural design
and object-oriented design.
In procedural design,
the system will focus
on structures and procedures.
Data is shared between procedures
and is accessible from all procedures,
even client procedures,
and procedures
know about the structure of data.
There is not this notion of late binding.
This means that
even if we can simulate it,
in fact, procedures
have different name
that are into a kind
of single namespace like in C.
And there is no decoupling
between messages and methods.
They are just procedures accessing data.
Let us take an example
to compare procedural modeling
and object-oriented modeling.
Imagine that we have a picture
which is composed of shapes,
like squares, rectangles and circles,
and we want to compute
the area of the picture.
In the procedural way,
and I wrote it in Java
because you can write,
in an object-oriented language,
in a procedural way,
what we will do is simple.
We will iterate over the list of shapes,
and for each shape,
we will check: "If there is a square,
then I know how to compute it.
It is width multiplied by width.
If there is a rectangle,
I have to multiply
the length by the height.
And if there is a circle,
I multiply pi by radius squared
and I am done."
We can also write that in Pharo.
I can iterate over the shape
and I do exactly the same.
And I check: "If this class
is from that kind, then I do that."
If this class is from that kind,
then I do that."
Now, what are the drawbacks?
There are several.
First, all the logic
is defined in one place,
which is not bad per say.
But the implications are bad.
I cannot reuse the main functionality.
What happens
if I want to add a new shape?
If I want to add a new shape,
I have to modify this method
or this procedure,
and I have to recompile it.
And I cannot even reuse
the main procedure.
Now, let us look at how this is done
in the OOP way.
In the OOP way, I will define the area
in the class "picture"
as a method,
and I will iterate over the shapes.
And I will ask each shape
to compute its own area.
And then, on square,
rectangle and circle,
I will define a method "area"
that computes its area.
What are the advantages?
Adding a new shape is really easy.
I just add a class
with the message "area" and I am done.
I can create objects and add
them to the diagram and I am done.
I can reuse the "Picture >> area" method.
There is no problem, because it is
independent of the shapes.
And then, we can see that there is
a decentralized view of computation.
Each shape represents
its own data/logic internally
and exposes just the area to the rest.
But there is a catch.
Imagine,
with object-oriented programming,
if we had not given the same name
to the method "area",
then, we could not reuse
the "Picture >> area" functionality
because then,
the client would have to check.
So, all the shapes
that offer the same service
agree to expose the same API,
the same interface to the client.
This is what is called "polymorphism".
This means that different objects
can answer the same message
with different executions.
This is really important,
because it is the way
to build good object-oriented design
by creating substitutable objects.
At the end, what is an application
in an object-oriented system?
An application is a collection
of interacting entities, objects.
Objects are characterized
by behavior and by state.
The state is private
and only methods can access the state.
Objects communicate by messages
that are resolved dynamically.
There is a distinction
between the messages
and the methods that are executed.
And message passing is late bound,
so it depends
on the receiver of the object
and the computation that is attached
to this object via its class.
What we saw is that objects
are unique entities.
They have a private state,
they react to messages,
and their methods perform computation.
The key point is that objects
should offer polymorphic interfaces
so that they can be mixed
with other objects
and that we can reuse
the code that used them.
Now, I would like to go
over three cornerstones
of object-oriented programming
and show the interplay between them.
The first two are encapsulation.
Encapsulation is the ability to hide
the way computation is done
and data is stored.
So, when I send a message, as a client,
I do not care about the way
my object manages data
and how computation is performed.
So, from that perspective,
if an object is composed
and delegates to other objects,
I am not impacted, as a client.
This means that the object
is free to decompose
its own computation into a subtask,
in a decentralized way.
This interplay with encapsulation
and composition is really important.
Then, there is another cornerstone,
the distribution of responsibility.
This means that when I compute a problem,
I decompose the problem into subtasks.
And this decomposition is emphasized
by the use of late binding,
where the idea is that the receiver
will decide what to do.
And these two things
are also further emphasized
by the idea of polymorphism.
Because I have objects
that exhibit the same interface,
then I can mix them together.
Because I have late binding,
then I can have polymorphism,
and then I can reuse objects
and build more modular applications.
The third cornerstone
that I have not presented yet
is an important one.
It is the idea that I can build,
in object-oriented programming,
abstraction
by extending other abstractions.
So, the point is that I can define
a class as a delta to another one.
For example,
if I have a "collection" class
that manages collections of objects,
then I can refine
this collection of objects
as "OrderedCollection",
because there is an order.
An "Array", for example,
can be a kind of collection.
And this mechanism
to define an abstraction
by specifying the delta
from one abstraction to another one
is called "inheritance".
Inheritance is super powerful
to reuse codes from superclasses.
Here, for example,
the code of collection will be reused
in "OrderedCollection" and "Array".
But I did not cover it in this lecture
because I will in another one.
So, what have we shown?
That with object-oriented programming,
programs are collaborating entities
that exchange messages,
that objects
encapsulate their private data,
that they can and should expose
polymorphic APIs or interfaces
so that they can be mixed
with other objects
and the client code can be reused.
And we saw that late binding
is a key aspect
that enables all this dynamic.
And at the end,
we get more modular applications.