Hello. Today, we will learn
about variables
and the types available in Pharo.
In fact, there are two big types:
local variables always start
with lowercase by convention;
we will see the local types available.
The second big group
is shared variables.
They start with uppercase by convention.
There are also several types.
Let's start with local variables
which start with lowercase.
Local variables have one method.
They are declared between pipes,
the vertical bars.
Here, there's a local variable, c:
it's local to the method
and exists only for its execution.
Therefore, it must always
start with lowercase.
By the way, all the class names
start with uppercase
because they are shared in the system.
Other types of local variables:
for example, there are
instance variables in the object
which are local to it.
There are two of them here: x and y.
They always start with lowercase.
As for local variables,
there are also
the methods' arguments, here.
In aPoint, "a" is lowercase.
because this variable
is also local to the method.
There are also block parameters.
For :x, x is a local variable
to a block.
A block argument, sorry.
So here, it starts with lowercase.
In Pharo, there are
six specific variables,
called special variables;
you can't change their names.
They are reserved words in Pharo.
There are more than 50 of them
in Java or JavaScript;
in Pharo, only six.
These are true, false, nil, self, super,
and thisContext.
Let's figure out
what these reserved words are for.
true and false
are instances of Booleans:
true is the unique instance
of the class True;
false, the unique instance
of the class False.
nil is the unique instance
of the class UndefinedObject.
So true, false, and nil
are objects like any other,
except they are the unique instances
of a specific class in the system.
Next, there are three pseudo-variables:
self refers to the current receiver,
and it's equivalent to this in Java.
super always refers
to the current receiver,
but this time, when you send
a message via super,
it means the method lookup,
the selection method algorithm,
which we will see in another class,
will start in the superclass
where the keyword super is written.
thisContext is a pseudo-variable
which refers to the object
that reifies the program's call stack.
It's an advanced concept
we'll study at the end of this MOOC.
We will explain it to you later.
For now, you just need to know
it's a pseudo-variable.
Now, shared or global variables.
First, you have all the classes.
All class names start with uppercase
because I can reference a class
from anywhere in the system.
Be careful: what starts
with uppercase is not always a class.
For example, Transcript:
it's an object name
shared in the system.
Everyone can reference this object.
And it's standard output,
stdout in other languages.
It's an instance object of a class,
globally accessible.
So its name starts with uppercase.
There are also class variables,
which are declared here when declaring
a class in classVariableNames;
here, the class #CombinedChar
defines two class variables,
one called Compositions
and the other Decompositions.
These two class variables
are accessible by the instances
of the class #CombinedChar
and of its subclasses.
That's why they're called
shared variables.
All the instances of the class
and its subclasses share them.
So both of them start with uppercase.
To summarize, you must remember:
all local variables, local to an object,
a block, or a method,
start with lowercase;
all global variables,
such as class names, etc.,
start with uppercase.