-Hi. In this video, we are going to look
at the class counterpart
of the implementors
and senders functionalities.
So, let's open
the System Browser once more.
So, Tools, System Browser,
go to AST-Core,
RBComment, for example,
or any other class.
You can right click on the class
and go to the Class references.
You can see that it even has
the same shortcut as the senders.
So, click on that.
You will have all the references
to the RBComment
that are made in bodies of methods
in the system.
Right there, we have four of them.
You can investigate them,
as with implementors and senders,
and another thing
is that this functionality is so useful
that it has
its own button in the interface.
So, right here, you can click on it
to open the same references.
Another important thing is,
when looking at instance variables,
you can highlight them.
Right click, go to Code search.
This will help you have access
to senders and implementors as well,
but most importantly,
to References to it.
If we look at it, there are basically
all the references
to the instance variable contents.
This will really help you understand
how the instance variable
is used within the class.
So, those functionalities
coupled with the ones of the methods
will really help you understand classes,
their architectures
and how they work together,
with the instance variables,
how they are sent,
and you can look for examples,
which is really important.
You can look for examples
using the senders functionality.
So, they have the same shortcut,
Cmd+N, to look at the references.
Or you can click on Class refs.
And if you want to look
for the references to instance variable,
Shift+Cmd+N
will open References to left.